<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A memorial humbly presented to the Right Honorable the Lord Chief Justice of the Kings-Bench in behalf of the hospitaller and his friends</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63911</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38920</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18189698</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18189698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63911)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1133:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A memorial humbly presented to the Right Honorable the Lord Chief Justice of the Kings-Bench in behalf of the hospitaller and his friends</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44], 26, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: John Turner.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hospitalers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MEMORIAL Humbly Preſented to the Right Honorable The Lord Chief Juſtice OF THE KING'S-BENCH In Behalf of the HOSPITALLER AND HIS FRIENDS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable Sir <hi>JOHN HOLT,</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice OF THE <hi>KING'S-BENCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe which was intended to be ſpoken to your Lordſhip in our common Defence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a full and clear Repreſentation of our Caſe, I do moſt humbly beſeech your Lordſhip, of your love to Juſtice, to accept and conſider, at your leiſure, on our behalfs. I had not been ſo hardy to take the part of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate upon me, but that I knew nothing when I began to write this, and till I had well nigh finiſh'd it, of the other Side's appearing by their Counſel againſt us, and then it was not for me to pretend to enter the Liſts with Men ſo uſed to Pleading, and ſo particularly Eminent and Learned in their Poſſeſſion as they are: however having written it at firſt to ſatisfie my ſelf and others as well as I could in the true Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Cauſe we were ingaged in; I have preſumed ſo far at this juncture, wherein our Affairs are haſtening to their
<pb facs="tcp:106987:3"/> 
               <hi>Criſis,</hi> as to publiſh and expoſe it to the open view of the World, becauſe it may be there may be ſome things in it, which even the ableſt Practiſer of the Long-Robe, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by ſo many Avocations, and full of other Thoughts and Buſineſs, might have omitted.</p>
            <p>Theſe Two things I humbly conceive to be very plain in it, Firſt, That the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London</hi> cannot reſtore the Ejected, whether Governors or Officers, without as plain and manifeſt a Diſpenſing Power, as that which even the late King aſſumed to himſelf; for if the Court of Aldermen may put out thoſe at pleaſure, whom the King by virtue of a Power given him by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Act of Parliament hath put into their reſpective Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and if they may reſtore thoſe whom he by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority hath legally ejected, what is this but at pleaſure to diſpenſe with the Act it ſelf? and to render ſuch a Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the King's behalf, as vain and fruitleſs as if it had never been made? What is it elſe but for the Court of Aldermen to challenge that exorbitant Privilege, as it's due, which is deny'd and barr'd by an expreſs Act of Parliament even to Kings themſelves, and all this for Cauſes ſo juſt and weighty, from the foreſight of the Miſchiefs which ſuch a Power <hi>may</hi> produce, and from the Experience of thoſe which it actually <hi>hath,</hi> that they carry their own Sanction included in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though no Act of Parliament to forbid or forecloſe the Exerciſe of a Power ſo Arbitrary and Boundleſs in it ſelf, and in its Conſequences ſo pernicious and deſtructive had ever been enacted? And whether a Court comparatively In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior, however otherwiſe deſerving a due Reverence and Reſpect from us, ought to be allowed to trample upon the juſt Authority of Kings, and to diſappoint the true meaning and intention of the High Court of Parliament it ſelf by any Order of theirs, is a thing that may deſerve your Lordſhip's
<pb facs="tcp:106987:3"/> Conſideration, and I doubt not, my Lord, but you will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly conſider it to our advantage, and for the reſtraining of a dangerous Power, which may diſpenſe with the whole Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Book, or with what part or parcel of it pleaſeth, as well as with any one Law.</p>
            <p>I know there are many very worthy Gentlemen in the Court of Adermen, that abhor the very thoughts of arrogating and aſſuming thus much to themſelves, many that are well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the neceſſary Regulations made in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. in which they themſelves were inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, being thereunto commiſſionated under the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and that it is only thoſe who are in truth no Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, that would be more than ſuch, if they knew how.</p>
            <p>The other thing, which to the beſt of my underſtanding, is every whit as clear as the former is, that if the Mayor or Court of Aldermen's Power (though it had been a legal Court of Aldermen, which the Act of Parliament hath declared at that time it was not) may over-rule the King's in our Caſe; then I cannot ſee that the Hoſpitals are his in any ſenſe, his Power and Prerogative in them will be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed, and he cannot ſo much as ſend a ſick Seaman or Soldier into any of theſe Houſes, without firſt asking leave of the City, which although, it may be, (eſpecially in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Circumſtances) they would not deny him, yet it is infinitely beneath the Majeſty of Princes to acknowledge or ſubmit to a precarious Dependence, wherever it can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they have a Right, even a private Perſon where he can make out his Title, would diſdain to aceept of his <hi>own</hi> upon theſe terms, by holding it only <hi>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ante beneplacito,</hi> by an uncertain, capricious and revocable Grant from another, and therefore it concerns all that love the Monarchy of <hi>England,</hi> and much more all thoſe that are under more particular Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to maintain and aſſert it, to ſee that its Honor and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> juſt Prerogative do not ſuffer in ſo important a Branch as this which concerns the Royal Hoſpitals, is, through the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes and Encroachments of a few Men, that aim at a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which they can never prove in the preſent Circumſtances to be their due.</p>
            <p>It is not their due in <hi>our</hi> Circumſtances, who were put in by the King, by whom the very Perſons whom they will needs reſtore were ejected, nor in <hi>theirs</hi> neither if it be true, that a certain Gentleman who takes much upon him, neither is nor ever was, ſince the avoidance of the Charter, a legal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of this Renowned City, and that ſeveral Aſſeſſors in the Court of Aldermen, have as little right to the Bench, as he hath to the Chair, a Controverſie, which in my ſmall Opinion, the Parliament hath determined already, or if they have not yet done it ſo clearly as might be wiſhed, yet in a ſhort time it may be hoped they will.</p>
            <p>In the mean while I cannot forbear ſaying, That I never ſaw leſs good Manners, leſs Decency, or leſs Modeſty in the Management of a Cauſe, than I have done in this, our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries have confeſs'd by an obſtinate and ſtubborn ſilence after ſo many fair Challenges and repeated Provocations, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Mercenary Pens that are always at their Service, that they have nothing to ſay for themſelves, and that both in Law and Equity it is a very plain Caſe againſt them: but yet ſtill they have a Confidence, not in their Cauſe, which they know to be very bad, but in their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which they perſuade themſelves is greater than the Power of Truth, that is proof againſt all this, they are reſolved upon their own Concluſion, and leave our naked Premiſes to ſhift for themſelves. Poor Premiſes! ſo deſtitute and ſo friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that even Hoſpitals refuſe them Entertainment.</p>
            <p>Nay, not only ſo, but when the Lords of the Council have been pleaſed to honor this little Cauſe of ours, little in its ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:106987:4"/> but in its Conſequences great, and worthy that Sacred and Majeſtick Board, with their ſublime and weighty Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, when they have referred the further Examination of it by an expreſs Order made in that behalf to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's known Wiſdom and untainted Juſtice, the reſult of which Enquiry is to be reported back again to them to put a final period and iſſue to it, which a Man would think in Reaſon ſhould have put a ſtop to any further Proceedings on their part, while the Affair was depending, out of a dutiful Reverence and Regard to that awful Judgment and Deciſion that was expected, yet even now do they go on, as they have always done, with taking it for granted that they are in the right, even now doth <hi>Hughes,</hi> in contempt of every thing that is Great or Good, in Defiance to all the moſt ſolemn Orders of Suſpenſion that can be made, and in Deſpite of his own recoiling and upbraiding Book, written againſt Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities and Non-Reſidence, before it happen'd to be his own Caſe, receive his quarterly Payments for doing nothing, while I have nothing but my labor for my pains; and while I have not wherewithal to defend their Majeſties Prerogative, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than with my Pen, which was a Reaſon of neceſſity why I ſhould plead my own Cauſe, and why I intended to do it in the following Remonſtrance; while I am intangled in Debt, and run into Extremities by a great deal of barbarous and unchriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage: My Adverſaries have the King's and the Hoſpital Revenues at their Service, to overthrow his Title and aſſert their own. So deeply rooted even in ſome that call themſelves Church men is the love of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth Intereſt, and a Diſſenting Party; ſo great is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a Sermon dedicated <hi>to his Excellency the Lord Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> in defence of the worſt Action that ever he did or could do by a Trooper formerly under his Command, by one that firſt fought againſt Monarchy with his Sword, then writ and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:5"/> preach'd and printed againſt it too, and was not content with Treaſon againſt the King without ſpitting his Venom againſt the Saint and the Martyr.</p>
            <p>My Lord, If <hi>Ludlow</hi> were ſo ſeverely and yet juſtly treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Reſentment of the Houſe of Commons, and if his Majeſty in Compliance with their humble Remonſtrance and Petition was pleaſed to iſſue out his Royal Proclamation for his Apprehenſion for High Treaſon wherever he could be found above forty Years after that Regicide was committed; <hi>Ludlow,</hi> that had but one Hand, one Finger in that fearful Crime; <hi>Ludlow,</hi> that had but one Voice in that execrable Doom, paſt by the vileſt of Traytors, and of Men upon the beſt of Kings. If he were forced to ſeek his Safety in his Flight; if he were neceſſitated to compound for a Life ſcarce worth the ſaving, after having lived ſo much beyond the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon periods of human Life, by a ſilent and voluntary Exile to Climes far diſtant from his native Country, to mountainous and barren Places, where Nakedneſs and Thirſt, and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reign, where Want and Beggery have their Habitation; then what doth he deſerve who by defending all the Regicides in what they had done, by ſtudied Blaſphemies and elaborate Harangues upon ſo horrid a Subject, hath pull'd down the Guilt of them all upon himſelf, and hath contracted their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Impieties into one, nay, hath done his utmoſt, which is worſt of all, to perſuade theſe Miſcreants as much as in him lay, not to repent and be ſorry for what they had done, and to encourage others to the like Attempts.</p>
            <p>The Act of Grace, my Lord, that hath remitted the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, hath not made the Fault leſs heinous than it was before; it is plain that his Caſe was rather more heinous than any of the Judges; and it is very ſtrange that this Man ſhould be thought to have a Right to eat the King's Bread, when others in Circumſtances ſcarce altogether ſo criminal as
<pb facs="tcp:106987:5"/> his, are forced in foreign Countries to beg their own, and glad that even that leaſt and laſt of Liberties belonging to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is not denied them by the purſuit of Juſtice, and the Anger of a People barbarouſly robb'd of an indulgent Father, a Wiſe, Religious, Chaſt, Temperate, Juſt, Merciful, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous and Heroick King, which neither time nor diſtance are able to appeaſe. Certainly the King hath either no power to viſit, though never ſuch Enormities be committed, though never ſuch perſonal Affronts be put upon him, as it was in Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Caſe, who preach'd and pray'd in this Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal as the King's Chaplain, when he was ſcarce qualified to breath in his Dominions, or to enjoy any benefit of a Subject; certainly the King's Hoſpitals are any bodies rather than the King's, or in this inſtance, at leaſt, he might exerciſe his Power, this was an allowable Cauſe of Viſitation.</p>
            <p>If the Mayor and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London</hi> had had in this Caſe an Authority ſo wholly independent on the King, as that his Majeſty could not by Law have interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in any Affair relating to the Hoſpitals of the City, yet the diſpoſal of the Officers of the ſaid Houſes, ſo as to retain and diſmiſs them at their pleaſure, being wholly Arbitrary and unaccountable in themſelves, without any remedy or appeal to an higher Power, or a ſuperior Court; It muſt needs have appeared to have been very hard, if they who might have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt a Servant or an Officer for no reaſon at all, would not have thought it reaſon ſufficient to diſcard any Man, that the King was diſpleas'd at him, that he look'd upon him as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to his Perſon or Government, that he had been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch things as had given juſt cauſe of Anger and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to his Majeſty againſt him; and the Hoſpital being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed on all hands to be a Royal Foundation, that Gratitude and Piety which was due to the Memory of the Royal Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, would have obliged the Truſtees in future Generations
<pb facs="tcp:106987:6"/> to have ſuch regard to his Succeſſors in the Throne, that his Requeſt ſhould be Sacred as to all thoſe things which they might lawfully have done without it, not only without the actual aſſignment of a Reaſon, but without the inward Power of being able to give one, if it were demanded: if muſt be confeſſed in this Caſe, that it would have been a great Affront, an unpardonable Contempt of Majeſty for Subjects to ſtand it out with their King, in a Matter wherein he thought his Honor intereſted and concerned, though he had nothing that could be called a Right; but when he himſelf by an Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſuperior to theirs, by his own Authority, by his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal, by a Right given and granted him by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it ſelf, hath diſplaced or ejected any Perſon in ſuch Circumſtances as theſe out of any Office or Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereof he ſtood formerly poſſeſſed; for a ſubordinate Power to pretend to reſtore ſuch an one in deſiance of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and unaccountable Right, and in Contempt of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which he vouchſaſes to aſſign, for which he did it: this certainly is ſo inſufferable, ſo inſupportable, ſo full of the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Indignity and Affront in Subjects to their Prime, that nothing can be more.</p>
            <p>Diſaffection to a Government, or Diſobedience to it, are very good Reaſons why a King ſhould viſit, wherever he hath a legal Power of Viſitation, becauſe the King is the Head of the Body Politick, and theſe are the greateſt political Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that can poſſibly be committed, and he muſt be the Judge who are diſaffected and who not, ſo far as concerns all Places of truſt and profit in his diſpoſal, wherein the preſent Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pants or Incumbents have only an Arbitrary, not a legal Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, otherwiſe he can never viſit at all upon any ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, unleſs thoſe to whom he muſt be ſuppoſed to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable in this Caſe ſhall concur with him in Judgment, that he hath good cauſe ſo to do, ſo that it is but the Court of
<pb facs="tcp:106987:6"/> Aldermen's firſt demanding his Reaſons, and then pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be diſſatisfied with them; and he hath effectually loſt his power of Viſitation.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, that all that were ejected in the late Viſitation of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. were Diſſenters, or at leaſt ſo great Favorites of that Intereſt and Party, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Conformity in their own Perſons, that they were rather more dangerous to the Government than the other: A Diſſenter, as ſuch, is one that ſeparates from the Eſtabliſh'd Worſhip and Communion for Conſcience ſake, which Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his is either real or pretended; if it be only a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conſcience, this Man in plainer terms is what we call an Hypocrite and a Knave, he plays a Game of Intereſt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be reveng'd of an whole Party for the ſake of ſome, againſt whom he hath conceiv'd an implacable Diſpleaſure, or becauſe he is of Opinion, and he may be extremely in the right ſo far, that it is for his advantage in point of Trade and Commerce to herd himſelf among the tender Conſciences, and the Men of Scruples, though he inwardly deſpiſe and laugh at them all this while, or elſe he deſigns to furniſh and enrich himſelf with the Spoils and Ornaments of Temples, and of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and with the Revenues of a Church, which are the firſt and laſt of his Objections, and afford his covetous and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Humor the beſt and the only Argument againſt it, or laſtly, he is one that being depreſt by the preſent poſture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and having a Mind too great for the meanneſs of his Fortune, will needs be ſhuffling the political Cards to try what new Game Confuſion will produce: And it is all one to him whether he raiſe himſelf upon the Ruins of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is by Law Eſtabliſh'd both in Church and State, or upon terms of Honor and Advancement from it, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelf neceſſary to its Preſervation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:7"/>
            <p>Theſe are four ſorts of Hypocritical Diſſenters, to which we might alſo add a fifth, that of a croſs-grain'd and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangl'd Tribe, whoſe Humor leads them naturally to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction and Strife; and who, for that Reaſon, are always againſt all things that have the publick Sanction on their Side; but that though there be nothing of Conſcience and Tenderneſs in ſuch an Humor as this, yet there ſeems to be a ſort of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in a peeviſh Temper, which is inconſiſtent with Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and Diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>But there is alſo the weak Brother, the real and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Separatiſt from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who is ſincerely of opinion that his Salvation lies at ſtake, and that he cannot comply with the Eſtabliſh'd Worſhip and Service, without a wilful hazarding his everlaſting Happineſs in the World to come, and a perpetual pain and diſquiet to his Conſcience in this, the Peace of which, though he may be under a ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Miſtake, is that which he ought certainly to prefer before any worldly advantage whatſoever, and the pains of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by a wilful Reſiſtance of its inward motions, though his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding all this while may be miſled and corrupted by Prejudice and Miſtake, are far more exquiſite and ſenſibly tormenting than the utmoſt Puniſhments that Law makers can invent, or Laws denounce, or Wit and Cruelty in confederacy together can inflict upon him.</p>
            <p>This ſort of Diſſenter therefore, as ſuch I believe there are many to be found, is a very proper Object of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion from us, as the other, whenever he is openly detected, is of our ſcorn and hatred; but ſtill we ought to be very cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and cautious in our Cenſures as to particular Perſons, notwithſtanding ſome failings, or wilful miſearriages altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconſiſtent with the Profeſſions which they make, which they may have afterwards repented of, and we are to judge the beſt, without notorious Evidence to the contrary; for the
<pb facs="tcp:106987:7"/> Peace of the World, which is embroil'd, and endanger'd by a cenſorious and reproachful Spirit, and for the quiet of our own Minds which is ſtrangely diſturbed by angry and uncharitable Opinions of other Men; only this in general we may ſay of all the Parties among us, even thoſe of the Eſtabliſh'd Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion not excepted, that while the belief and hope of another World, is every where pretended, it is the Enjoyment of this, and the Gratification of the Deſires and Appetites belonging to it, that is every where chiefly ſought after.</p>
            <p>But of all Men there are none that may be more juſtly or more ſafely cenſur'd, than thoſe that look one way while they row another, that pretend to be ſtrict Members of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Communion, and yet make it their ſtudy under that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe to do it all the miſchief they can, and to encourage and abet the ſeparating Parties in their Deſigns againſt it, for nothing is more plain than that this Man hath added Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to Hypocriſie, the moſt exquiſite Hatred to the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and criminal Diſſimulation, that he lies in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that he may the more ſecurely deſtroy, without giving warning of the Blow before it comes, or owning ſo much as a ſincere Enmity, or a frank and fair Intention of Revenge.</p>
            <p>Now this is common to all the ſeveral Parties of Diſſenters from our Church, and of thoſe that favor and abet them in diſguiſe, that they all aim at an Eccleſiaſtical and a Civil Commonwealth, and their Principles even among thoſe that are moſt honeſt and conſcientious in them, do naturally aim at the Subverſion both of Church and State, as to the preſent Eſtabliſh'd Conſtitution of them: for Church and State, tho they be two things, yet they both conſiſt and are made up of the ſame Perſons, and the nature of Government is the ſame in both, and it is an Agreement between the Modes and Forms of Government in the Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, that makes each of theſe moſt firm, ſtrong and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:8"/> laſting in it ſelf, and alſo moſt uſeful and ſerviceable to the other.</p>
            <p>It is certain, that he that in his Scruples is really Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious, he that hath all that tenderneſs of Senſe, that nicety of Palate in matters of Religion to which he outwardly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, he looks upon the Liturgy and Ceremonies by Law Eſtabliſh'd, and upon the Hierarchy or ſubordinate Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this wiſely conſtituted Church, with all the Averſion which we have for Idolatry it ſelf, or for the moſt groſs and palpable Superſtition of which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is guilty at this day. He that pretends the ſame Scruples but really hath them not doth all the ſame things, as to any outward appearance that the other doth; and his Thoughts not being buſied about the other World, which he looks upon as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and an uncertain thing, (and perhaps obſerving the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intrigues and Policies of all Parties, while Heaven and Conſcience is every where pretended; he is the more harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Contempt of every thing that is good or ſacred) this Man's immediate and direct aim, without any reſpect to his Happineſs or Miſery in a future State, is at the Ruin of that Eſtabliſhment, (for Reaſons of Intereſt, or out of Envy, Pride, or a new fangl'd Temper, that is always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie under preſent things) from which he pretends to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate for Conſcience ſake. Laſtly, he that in his own Perſon conforms to the Eſtabliſhment, but in his practice under I know not what healing, uniting, and moderate Pretences, is always a faſt Friend to the Diſſenting Parties, making uſe of all the Power and Intereſt he hath to advance their Credit, and to encreaſe their weight in the political Balance; he is manifeſtly got into a triple League with the other two, and he is much the moſt dangerous Confederate of the three, becauſe he is an Enemy in our own Quarters, an Adverſary in the diſguiſe and habit of a Friend, a Traytor that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays
<pb facs="tcp:106987:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> and crucifies with a Kiſs, and makes a ſhew of great Zeal for the good of that Eſtabliſhment, which he deſigns to ruin and overthrow.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more certain than that all theſe ſeveral ſorts of Men do agree at the long run at the Subverſion of the Monarchy it ſelf, or whatever they may ſay or ſuggeſt in excuſe of themſelves, or to palliate ſo foul and true an Accuſation; yet it is certain in the Experience of this and other Nations: that the Monarchy cannot ſubſiſt where Prelacy is deſtroy'd; and I wiſh ſome new Experiment of Diſciplinarian Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practices in our own Age may not further convince us of the truth of this, for we have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> already, paſt Experiences do ſufficiently aſſure us, what the Event of ſuch Practices and Deſigns muſt be, where they have ſcope and liberty enough allowed them, and now I pray God thoſe old Confuſions may never riſe from the dead to convince us, that the ſame Cauſes, the ſame Paſſions, Deſigns and Intereſts, let alone to themſelves and purſued into their Conſequences, will everlaſtingly produce the ſame effects.</p>
            <p>Nay, in Reaſon, my Lord, as well as in Experience, there is nothing more plain, if we argue forward from the Cauſe to the Effect, than that the Demolition of the Hierarchy and its Dependences together with it, which all of them have their firſt Spring and Fountain in the Crown, muſt be the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it of ſo many Friends, and by Conſequence of ſo much Power; it not only throws a powerful and certain Intereſt, as it were by way of ſcramble, among the People, but by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arming and diſabling the circumvented Prince, whoſe true Greatneſs conſiſts in the multitude of thoſe whoſe Intereſt it muſt always be to be his Friends, it arms and ſets up a Commonwealth Party againſt him at his own Charge, and we know in days of yore, when the Biſhops were once gone, the next thing complain'd of was the Houſe of Lords, and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:9"/> then the King himſelf was an inſupportable Grievance, and all Orders and Degrees of Men amongſt us, all that had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Honeſty or Money and were diſſatisfied with ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, or were ſuſpected or repreſented ſo to be, or had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in the defence of their Religion and Country were plundered, ſequeſter'd, baniſh'd, and what not; as if the way to reform were to deſtroy, and the only means to make a Nation glorious and happy, were by oppreſſing it and tearing it in pieces.</p>
            <p>But, my Lord, I ſhall not lanch out any further into theſe things, only what I have ſaid was in order to ſhew the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why that Wiſe Prince and Excellent Perſon, King <hi>Charles</hi> II. made his Royal Viſitation by his Commiſſioners under the Broad-Seal in this Houſe, and why he thought fit to eject ſo many out of it, and to deprive them of all Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Authority, or Concern in it, both among the Officers and the Governors themſelves, becauſe he knew many of them to be profeſt Diſſenters, or which is all one, Enemies to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and Friends to no political Intereſt but a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; and he ſuſpected others not to be ſo good as they ſhould be, and his Suſpicion muſt be allowed to be a very good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Places at his own diſpoſal, when himſelf is the Judge without controul or appeal of the fitneſs reſpectively of every Perſon for them.</p>
            <p>He had Reigned very happily for many years, with uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Peace and ſatiating Plenty, belov'd by his Subjects, and dreaded by his Neighbors round about, as Glorious and as Great in all reſpects as a great Fortune added to a great Mind could make him; and if we inquire into the Reaſons of this wondrous Calm, thoſe Halcyon Days, and Bleſſed Years that followed the Storms and Tempeſts of the late bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and bloody <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, it can be imputed ſo proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to no human means, as to his Reſtoring and Re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:106987:9"/> the Church in its ancient Beauty, Order, Purity and Splendor, and to his aſſerting it and defending it againſt all its Enemies by good and wholſom Laws; but when for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which I do not meddle with, and which I cannot approve, he thought fit to lay the reins upon the Diſſenters Necks by a Toleration granted without Act of Parliament, and to let them take their full ſwing of liberty in Religious Matters, inſomuch that the Parliament then thought it neceſſary, as well to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their own Authority, and to quaſh this Attempt at a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power, as for other Conſiderations, which they had before them, to get the Declaration of Indulgence cancell'd and withdrawn; yet from that time there was every where to be ſeen a virtual, though not an explicit and declared In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and the numbers of Diſſenters were every where ſo conſiderable, that if they were but kept out of all places of Truſt and Conſequence in the Kingdom; Reaſon of State might even then have required, that ſo numerous a Party ſhould be conſidered as to the liberty of their Conſciences, and as to the outward exerciſe of their Religion, with an Indulgence ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Publick Sanction, upon which they might ſafely rely, and not have the Oppreſſion of their Conſciences, or the Fears of it, to urge for a Pretence to juſtifie or palliate Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon any future occaſion, but this, though it was not then granted, yet if it had, it would not have ſerved the turn as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by this, that to get into Employments and Publick Truſts in the Kingdom, their Caſuiſts had ſtarted a new ſort of Divinity among them, and made it lawful to ſerve the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and Deſigns of their Party, which can be nothing elſe when their Scruples are indulged, but the getting of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment into their own hands, by telling them as to Oaths, which it was preſumed by the Authority that enjoin'd them, ſuch Perſons would not take, that they were to be taken not in the ſenſe of the Impoſers, but of the takers themſelves, and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo every Oath was either altogether uncertain, that is vain and of no force at all, or it had as many Meanings as there could be private Interpretations made, or it was taken with the Proviſo's and Limitations of the Caſuiſts of the Party, who would be ſure ſo to order the matter, as not to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of any Office or Employment by any Oath or Teſt that could be put upon them: and as for Oaths, ſo alſo for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, they could not digeſt it upon every ordinary occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the uſage and practice of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but when the Receiving after that manner was made a Qualification for every publick Employment, then they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd very nicely betwixt the Religious Act and the Civil, or Political Qualification, they look'd upon it only as a civil Thing, a political Formality, a pre-requiſite <hi>Agendum</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd by the Laws of their Country, in order to qualifie and prepare them, for their reſpective Offices and Employments, the better to ſerve their own Party, and to do miſchief to the Government in them, without any regard to the Religious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, comprehended under that awful and bleſſed Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>And as ſome did by occaſional Communion, ſo others did by conſtant, and were great Zealots for the Eſtabliſh'd Church, conſtant frequenters of the Divine Service and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, only to let them into Opportunities, as appeared by the Event; <hi>For the tree is known by its fruits,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb and overturn it, by favoring and abetting as much as in them lay all the Deſigns and Practices of the Separating Parties.</p>
            <p>This being therefore an extraordinary Diſeaſe, to which no ordinary Remedies could be apply'd with ſucceſs; for what can bind or tie up the hands of ſuch Men whom nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Oaths nor Sacraments are able to oblige. It was judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe that were then at the Helm of Affairs, that ſome extraordinary and unuſual Courſe muſt be taken, to hinder
<pb facs="tcp:106987:10"/> theſe profligate and wicked Principles, ſo deſtitute of the fear of God, and ſo deſtructive of all Faith and Society among Men, from having thoſe miſchievous Effects upon the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for which they were deſigned, and this at length ended in the ſeizure of ſo many Charters into the King's hands, and in his new modelling all Corporations at Diſcretion; diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all ſuch at his pleaſure, as he had any proof of Diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or any ground of Jealouſie againſt, and placing others in their ſtead, in whom he might better confide.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not go about to defend the Legality of ſuch a Courſe as this; if the neceſſity of it will not defend it nothing will, for that there was a neceſſity of ſomething extraordinary at that time to be done is apparent, and what was done had really this good Effect, that the Government was generally ſpeaking put into better hands, the Republican Faction were every where diſcouraged, and the Monarchy and Church were ſet upon a firmer bottom than they had ſtood upon for many Years before: ſo that if this turn of State were in it ſelf illegal, yet it cannot be deny'd, but it had wholſom Effects; and what with this and the legal Penalties which were then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and the many excellent Diſcourſes publiſhed by our Clergy, to ſatisfie the Scruples, and rectifie the Miſtakes and Miſapprehenſions of the Diſſenters; things were now arrived to a very great degree of compoſure, and the Schiſm was now in a very fair probability of moldering into nothing.</p>
            <p>This preſent Parliament, however diſſatisfied with ſuch Proceedings, as ſupported barely by the King's Prerogative without any conſent of theirs, and being look'd upon perhaps, as I am perſuaded it was, as a deſign, among other things, to model Parliaments at the pleaſure of the Court; and for that Reaſon ſuch a general Disfranchiſement of the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, muſt needs in its Example and Conſequence at leaſt be a thing very dangerous to the liberty of the Subject, as
<pb facs="tcp:106987:11"/> it proved afterwards in the late King's Reign, when the Corporations were put into the hands of Diſſenters and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: yet notwithſtanding conſidering what ſort of Men they were that were at that time put into publick Truſts, and how well the Corporations, as obnoxious to and dependent upon the Crown as they were, did afterwards acquit themſelves in the beginning of the late King's Reign, by ſending ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives to Parliament, as approved themſelves upon the ſevereſt tryals to be ſo true to the Eſtabliſh'd Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to the liberties of the People, by refuſing to revoke the Teſt and Penal Laws, and by a bold and generous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning of the Diſpenſing Power, for which they were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſolved, as unfit and unſerviceable for the preſent turn, but alſo put out of all places of truſt, honor, profit and power through the Nation; I ſay, for theſe Reaſons, and out of a juſt reſpect to the Eternal Merit of ſo much Virtue, Integrity and Courage in a critical and dangerous Juncture; the Parliament were ſo well ſatisfied and pleas'd with them, that they would not ſuffer them to be call'd in queſtion, and much leſs would they be perſuaded to render them incapable of any future Service, for ſo many Years together, as would have put the whole Power of the Nation effectually into ſuch hands, as in all likelihood would have alter'd the Government both in Church and State, and ſecured a perpetual Republick to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>It is our Saviour's own Rule, that <hi>a Kingdom or an Houſe divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> not but that in <hi>this Kingdom</hi> or <hi>this Houſe,</hi> there may be divers Opinions, and yet the Peace of them both may be maintain'd, either by Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity on the one hand, or by putting the whole Power of this Kingdom or this Houſe into the hands of one ſort, who want not ſufficient means to defend themſelves, and to keep the reſt from doing them or one another any conſiderable harm on the
<pb facs="tcp:106987:11"/> other; but where not only Opinions, but alſo Powers are divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, where they that ſeparate in Opinion from the reſt, are ſharers in the Civil Power together with them, there being no uſe of Power but for Defence or Annoyance, it is impoſſible but a divided Power muſt be proportionably weakened, but that Powers mixt that are imploy'd upon different Deſigns muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a dangerous Ferment, and that Powers divided and bent againſt each other muſt break and ſhatter one another's Strength; the Conſequence of all which is, that when diverſity of Opinions concerning matters of Religion or Government produceth State Factions and Parties in a Nation, there the Peace of that Nation cannot be preſerved, but by putting the Civil Power entirely into the hands of one of them, and in this caſe that Party hath the greateſt right, nay, it is a ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Law of Nature, it is an Eternal Law of human Society ſuppoſing it once to ſubſiſt. that that Party ſhould have the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent over the reſt, which by its ſtrength and credit is the beſt able to preſerve it ſelf, and to protect the reſt, and which the reſt may live the moſt eaſily and happily under; but let it be how it will where there are ſeveral Parties, it is neceſſary for the quiet of the World, and for the end of Government which is Peace, that one Party ſhould have the Government over the reſt, and (beſides the aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed hopes and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a future and a better Life,) upon this very political Principle it was, that the Primitive Chriſtians endured the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt Perſecutions and the utmoſt Cruelties without the leaſt thought of Reſiſtance, it being better for the Civil Intereſt, and for the temporal Quiet and Happineſs of this World, which good Men ought to prefer upon a publick Principle before any thing perſonal and belonging to themſelves, that even the beſt of Men ſhould ſuffer by Injuſtice, than that the State ſhould be endangered or embroiled by a tumultuous Endeavor to free our ſelves from the Tyranny of the Laws, when ever they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb facs="tcp:106987:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> to patronize the wrong ſide, as in many Countries they have always done.</p>
            <p>Again, Where there is a Balance betwixt the contending Parties, or very nigh the matter, if we were to proceed by the Poll, there ſtill it is a Law of Nature in the ſecundary Senſe, it is a ſtanding Law and Rule of human Society, that one of the Parties is to govern, the other to obey, becauſe a mixture of both in places of truſt and profit, will through the interfering Appetites and Deſigns of Men, and through the ridiculous and ſuperſtitious Fondneſs which moſt Men for want of Philoſophy and Charity have entertained for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Opinions; it cannot fail but the Powers of ſuch a Government will bulge upon each other and fall foul upon themſelves. Its Laws and Edicts cannot have that force and efficacy which they ſhould have, becauſe ſuch a Government hath divers Wills which cannot all be obey'd, and wants an uniform and ſteady Principle of Jurisdiction within it ſelf, whereby to exact and force Obedience to its commands.</p>
            <p>Where the Balance as to number is in a manner equal there the Party that is in Poſſeſſion hath the right, becauſe a real Poſſeſſion of Offices of Truſt and Profit, and which is more, of Arſenals, Magazines, and Places of ſtrength, of Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and Military Stores, and of the Ports and Naval Forces belonging to a Nation is ſuch a vaſt addition of ſtrength, though without number, to the one Party, that it is in vain and againſt the great Law of Self-Preſervation for the other to contend: it is their trueſt Intereſt to ſubmit to them, provided they may purchaſe their Safety by their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and that though they be excluded from any ſhare in the Government, yet they are not deny'd the juſt liberties of Subjects, and have ſuch a Security as may be depended upon for their Perſons and Eſtates.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:12"/>
            <p>But here when I ſpeak of <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> and of <hi>Right,</hi> I mean, <hi>ſuch</hi> a Right and <hi>ſuch</hi> a Poſſeſſion as is Eſtabliſh'd by Law, according to the uſual Methods and Formalities by which the Laws of any Country are enacted, for all other ſtrength be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this is not properly <hi>poteſtas</hi> but <hi>latrocinium;</hi> it is a perpetual State of Violence and Piracy upon the People, and they who have the Laws on their ſide, though they ſhould want other defences, are naturally bold and daring, their Complaints and Remonſtrances will be always more or leſs conſidered and reflected upon even by their Enemies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whereas a Party that uſeth force in Oppoſition to a legal Right, is always ſuſpicious and timorous of it ſelf, it hath always many Deſerters that will be ſtraggling from it, many ſecret Enemies harboring within its boſom, many Fears and Jealouſies which rebate its edge and weaken its Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and rob it of that Truſt and Confidence within it ſelf, which is always of neceſſity required to its Preſervation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, In ſuch a caſe where a Nation conſiſts of ſeveral divided Parties, and one of them able to poiſe and balance all the reſt, there that is the Party that for the ſafety of the whole, hath the moſt natural and unqueſtionable right to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, and if to this natural Right, reſulting from its weight and number, there be added a legal Poſſeſſion of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; this ſtrengthens the natural by a poſitive or civil Title, and is the ſame ſort of Right by which every Man holds his own, and if its Frame and Conſtitution within it ſelf be ſuch, as gives it the greateſt fitneſs to govern and to preſerve the Peace and Tranquillity of a Nation; here is an intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Dignity and Worth belonging to it, added to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Circumſtances of number and Poſſeſſion, that finiſhes and completes this Right of preſiding with Authority and Juriſdiction over all the reſt, and gives the laſt ſtrokes of Brightneſs and Perfection to it: Now this, my Lord, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly
<pb facs="tcp:106987:13"/> the Caſe of the legal Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with reſpect to all the ſeparating and diſſenting Parties amongſt us; Firſt, In number it equals, nay, I hope it exceeds and over-balances all the reſt; Secondly, It hath the publick Sanction on its ſide, and is put into the Poſſeſſion of the Government by the Laws; and Thirdly, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reſpect its Principles which are mild and moderate, and have a noble mixture of the Gentleman and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in them, or its Government which conſiſts in a comely, beautiful and regular Subordination, in which Majeſty, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, and Strength, a graceful Hew, an healthful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, a firm and well-compacted Organization are united; there can be no Eſtabliſhment that is more fit to govern con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in it ſelf, or is more able in the firſt place to ſecure its own peace and ſafety, and in the next to diffuſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate thoſe bleſſings to all the ſeveral Parties of the Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by taking even thoſe into its Guard and Protection, who will not admit of its more cloſe Embraces, and refuſe to be warm'd and cheriſhed in its boſom, whereas if Power be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently lodged in Men of all Perſuaſions, it is impoſſible that any one Party ſhould be ſafe, but the Vibration of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts by giddy and uncertain Motions, and the mixture of Powers that are at ſtriſe and enmity with each other, will make every party diffident of it ſelf; apprehenſive of its fel. lows, inſatiably thirſty of the Sovereign Power, which only can free it of its Fears and Dangers, and will infallibly produce ſome publick and inteſtine Commotions, if ſeaſonable and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Remedies be not applied.</p>
            <p>And as the Church of <hi>England</hi> is that Conſtitution, which is the beſt able to ſtand upon its own bottom, and to give Protection to the Parties diſſenting from it, ſo is it alſo that Eſtabliſhment whether we conſider its Doctrine or its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, its inward Sentiments, or its outward Polity,
<pb facs="tcp:106987:13"/> which is the trueſt Friend and Supporter of the Crown, it is that without which the Monarchy can no more ſubſiſt, than a Candle can burn without Flame, than a Lamp can be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd without Oil, or a Fire ſubſiſt without Heat; ſo that every Diſſenter who envys at the Hierarchy, or endeavors to level the Eccleſiaſtical State into a new Model of his own or his Teacher's making, does by robbing the Crown of its beſt and moſt powerful Friends, its moſt faithful, ſteady and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Champions and Defenders: leave it to the mercy of Republican Deſigns, and expoſe it to the Rage and Fury of the worſt of Men; every Diſſenter is either an Enemy to Monarchy, or he does not underſtand his own Principles, if he be not, (and this I believe to be the Caſe of very great numbers amongſt them,) for his Principles and Models of Government in the Church will as certainly deſtroy and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Monarchy in the State, as Fire will melt Wax, or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter extinguiſh Fire; So that I take a Diſſenter and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealthſman to be in a manner convertible terms, and that no conſidering Man can pretend with a ſafe Conſcience that Epiſcopacy is unlawful, but he muſt own with the ſame breath that Monarchy is ſo too; for theſe two things will always have ſuch a Connexion, that it will be impoſſible to ſeparate the one of them from the other, neither can any Man who is a Friend to his Prince, be an Enemy to the Grandure of the Eccleſiaſtical State, though it were indeed much greater, and more invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than it is.</p>
            <p>There is no one Party of the Separation that will pretend to vie Strength or Intereſt with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all united in confederacy together, and in favorable Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures to wicked. Deſigns and Men, when the People are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, the State is troubled, and Animoſities are grown high, and in a manner incurable betwixt the King and his two Houſes, they may and they have actually deſtroy'd and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown
<pb facs="tcp:106987:14"/> it, as it happened in the late times in the troubleſome and diſtemper'd Reign of King <hi>Charles I.</hi> but when that work is done, they cannot all Rule together, and they have no one Party that is fit to govern the reſt; the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> who are perhaps the fitteſt to govern of all the Diſſenting Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were the firſt that leap'd into the empty Saddle, but they wanted an <hi>Academy</hi> to teach them to ride, for they could not ſit long there, but were diſmounted with Contempt and Scorn by the growing Intereſt of the Independent Party, the rigor of their Diſcipline would not be endured, the Meanneſs of their Perſons was deſpiſed, and their whole Management was ſo diſtaſtful, that it hath made them odious to the beſt and wiſeſt part of the Nation ever ſince, they wanted the two things without which it will be always impoſſible to govern; Sirength on the one ſide and Reverence on the other; to make amends for which defect, and to reconcile the People to the new Model, by making them Parts of the Building, and Sharers in the Adminiſtration of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs; the Lay-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were called in, and they, as is uſual for Men of Mechanick and frequently even ſor did Education, when they are gotten into power, were the moſt inſolent, intolerable and inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able People in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Presbytery</hi> either emergeth out of the ſtate of Parity, which is a State of Force and Rigor, that hath no Reverence for its own Authority, and is uneaſie under its own Bonds, into the noble and only natural ſtate of an Epiſcopal Subordination; (for Government and Subordination, the ſeveral degrees of the one and of the other, and the Perfection of them both, are indeed but the ſame things under ſeveral and diſtinct Names,) or elſe it drops downwards into Independency, that is diſtinct and ſeparate Aſſemblies without any common appeal amongſt them all, which is the laſt and moſt imperfect ſtate of human Society, whether in Sacred or in Civil Bodies, and is the next ſtep to
<pb facs="tcp:106987:14"/> Confuſion, if it be not Confuſion it ſelf, out of which, as from a Chaos, weary of it ſelf and of its own dark, diſtracted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered Nature, a new World of Beauty and of Order doth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ariſe, and from the Inconveniences, the endleſs Troubles, the wild Enthuſiaſms, the mad and extravagant Perplexities and Tormoils of ſuch a State; at length it comes to paſs that the Spirit of God begins to move upon the face of the Waters and Light to flutter with uncertain motions, and with a gloomy and imperfect Beam, till Monarchy and Prelacy the two great Lights, the Sun to Rule the Paſſions and Appetites of the Day, the Moon to diſpel the Ignorance and Darkneſs of the Night, begin to rouſe their drooping and diſconſolate Heads, as they did at the end of our late unhappy Confuſions, and like the Phenix burnt in its own ſpicy Neſt, to revive thoſe Odors and retrieve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves into a new vigorous and fragrant Life, gaining new Strength, and Youth, and Beauty, from their Ruins: for this is, and will always be, the ſtanding nature of things, that as order degenerates through careleſsneſs or through deſign into Confuſion; ſo Confuſion muſt either end in abſolute Deſtruction, or retrieve it ſelf back again into neceſſary Order, and there being but two ways to keep Mankind in Obedience, that is, either by Force or Perſuaſion, Force is an uncertain and capricious thing, and where it conquers moſt, its conqueſt is imperfect, becauſe it hath no empire over the Will, in the Obedience of which alone it is, that any Empire or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſecure, and Perſuaſion without Force will ſcarce do ſo much as Force without Perſuaſion, amongſt ſo many obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and perverſe Wills as every Government is to work upon for its own Peace and Safety, but it is a willing Fear, a Fear mixt with Reverence and blended with Love, it is wholeſom Laws enforced by a comely and ſubordinate dependence of all the parts of a Government upon each other, and recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the greatneſs and dignity of the Perſons with whom the
<pb facs="tcp:106987:15"/> Execution of them, whether in Sacred or in Civil Matters, is intruſted, it is a certain mixture by wiſe and juſt Proportions of theſe two Principles together, ſo as to render Diſobedience not only unſafe, but alſo unreaſonable and inexcuſable too, and to enforce Obedience by the Beauty and Majeſty, and wiſe Contexture of that Government to which it is pay'd, that when all is done is the only true Elixir of Life, and the beſt Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to make any Body or Community of Men both firm and happy, to ſecure it the moſt effectually from inteſtine Maladies, and external Dangers, and make it pleaſed and contented within it ſelf.</p>
            <p>That Form of Government is certainly the beſt, whether in Church or State, which gives the greateſt Encouragement to Virtue and to Merit, and propounds the faireſt hopes to great Minds, to animate and inſpire them with an impatient Conſtancy in the purſuit of Praiſe, through all the Fatigues and Difficulties that attend it; and this without queſtion is the ſubordinate Form, as well in Church as State, wherein a Scale of Honor is propounded, and every new ſtep, as it is a Reward of paſt Endeavors, ſo is it a ſtrong Incitement for the future, to go on in the ſame Courſes with new and daily Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of Wiſdom and of Virtue to our lives end; this gives Authority and Reputation to a Church, and makes its Laws more eaſie by the Reverence which is paid to thoſe with whom the Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline is intruſted, it refines and ſublimates, by the Example and Doctrine of its Teachers, the Genius of a Nation, whoſe true Pride and Ornament conſiſts in the Exaltation of thoſe Faculties, and in the Exerciſe of thoſe Moral Virtues, by which we are Men, and by which we differ from the Beaſts that periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> cannot be a true and perfect Conſtitution, where Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Philoſophy, for want of ſufficient Encouragement in the Proſecution of them, are firſt of mere Neceſſity diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:106987:15"/> (Mens Minds being ſunk into a proportionable degree of Poverty with their Fortunes and their Hopes) and then by way of plea for Ignorance, decry'd; nor <hi>that</hi> where the unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rigors of Diſcipline are ſuch that they deſtroy the true Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and innocent Divertiſements of human Converſation, Nor laſtly <hi>that,</hi> which by Hypocriſie or ſomething very like it, by uncouth Formalities, and uneaſie Affectations renders it ſelf nauſeous, to the beſt and wiſeſt part of Mankind, to Men of the beſt Principles, and to the moſt candid and ingenuous Tempers belonging to a Nation, to the Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdom in particular, and to all the Men of frank and liberal Education, who will never endure that intolerable Yoak of Phariſaick Righteouſneſs, and Saucy Rigor, that turns Men either into Hypocrites or Fools, and makes them look as if they were bewitch'd or enchanted, to ſit upon their Necks, but will be ſure to ſhake it off, and free themſelves from under its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable preſſures with all the Indignation and Scorn which it deſerves.</p>
            <p>To conclude this matter therefore, the Church of <hi>England</hi> among all the ſeveral Parties and Diſtinctions that are amongſt us, is ſingly and alone that Body of Men to which the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the reſt is due, whether we conſider the greatneſs of its numbers, the extent and wideneſs of its Intereſt and Power, the Wiſdom and Moderation of its Principles and Doctrines, the Candor and more than uſual Humanity and Ingenuity of its Members, the learning and univerſally acknowledged Merit and Dignity of its Paſtors, the Strength and Beauty of its ſubordinate Conſtitution, its agreeableneſs to Monarchy, and to the Genius and Temper of the beſt and wiſeſt part of the Nation among all Ranks and Qualities whatſoever; all other Parties may be ſhaded and protected by this and kept from annoying it or one another, ſuppoſing all Offices of publick Truſt; and all things that belong to the Exerciſe of Power be put into
<pb facs="tcp:106987:16"/> its hands, but without it, it is impoſſible they ſhould all be ſafe and ſcarce any one of them would be able to ſubſiſt, which thing if all the honeſt part of the Diſſenters would ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, they would be content, with the liberty of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which without Neceſſity ought not to be denied them, that is, with all that liberty of Action and Profeſſion in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligous Matters which they do not abuſe to the prejudice of their Neighbor or the Publick, without pretending to any ſhare in the Government, which in a Monarchy cannot ſubſiſt upon their terms, but is greatly endangered, though but by a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſuch, or their notorious Abetters in it, and if nothing but the Government will ſerve their turn, notwithſtanding all the other Bleſſings and Privileges of Subjects, whether they be of a Temporal or a Spiritual Nature, which they are allowed to enjoy, they cannot in reaſon expect in this caſe to be treated as Men of tender Conſciences, but of ſeditious Tempers, and as Diſturbers of the publick Peace, which by ſuch turbulent and ambitious Practices they go about to undermine, and to confirm us in an Opinion, which for my part I have always entertained concerning the Men of the beſt Parts and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among them, that a Diſſenter and a Commonwealths-man hardly differ ſo much as the two <hi>Amphytruoes</hi> or the two <hi>Soſiaes</hi> in <hi>Plautus;</hi> for they, though they were very like, yet they were not the ſame; neither in all this have I ſaid any more than what the Wiſdom and Authority of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will juſtifie me in, for they though they have granted an univerſal Indulgence to all the Proteſtant Denominations among us, yet they have not taken off thoſe Teſts, which will effectually ſecure all that are not openly falſe and treacherous to their own avowed Principles among them, from having any ſhare in any Publick Truſt, or in any matter of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or State.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:16"/>
            <p>I have inſiſted the more largely upon this weighty Subject concerning the neceſſity of there being one Governing Party in a Nation, where there are ſeveral differing and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with each other, as to their Sentiments in Religion, or as to their Notions of Government, whether by a Monarchy or a Commonwealth, that I might repreſent in as clear a Light as my Meanneſs would permit; the Reaſons of State that moved that diſcerning Prince K. <hi>Charles II.</hi> to take ſo extraordinary and unuſual Meaſures in the regulating and new modelling the Corporations of <hi>England;</hi> which being now confeſſed on all hands to have been very <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwarrantable, Arbitrary, and Illegal, it hath derived no ſmall Prejudice upon ſome other Affairs, which though legal in themſelves, were yet not only conſequent upon it in point of Time and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but perhaps if it had not been for the aforeſaid Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had never been tranſacted; and ſuch the Viſitation of the Hoſpitals ſeems to have been.</p>
            <p>For my own part, my Lord, I am very clearly of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Seizure and Avoidance of the Charters, and the almoſt forceable Surrenders that were made, however it might be done for Reaſons of Publick Good, ſo far as the preſent Turn was concerned, yet in the way of doing it by the ſole Authority and Prerogative of the Prince, through almoſt all Corporations, almoſt at the ſame time, it was altogether Arbitrary and Illegal, and that in its Conſequences, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſufficiently in the next Reign; it was pernicious and deſtructive to that very Deſign for which it was firſt made uſe of, when by the very ſame Power, added to that other of diſpenſing with Teſts and Penal Laws, the Corporations were ſo regulated, that Papiſts and Diſſenters were almoſt the only Men that were truſted or employed, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all Places was put into ſuch Hands as the Law had expreſly and ſollicitouſly precluded from having any ſhare
<pb facs="tcp:106987:17"/> in the Publick Adminiſtration; not that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> had any ſuch real Tenderneſs for the Diſſenters, or that they on the other ſide by all the Careſſes and Endearments in the World, could be brought off from their deſerved Averſions to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but in this common Deſign they both agreed, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> must down; and then a new Tryal of Skill would have ſucceeded, which of theſe two ſhould be triumphant at last, and trample upon the other after all this Fawning and Friendſhip: the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who can never tolerate but when it is not in their Power to puniſh, relyed upon the Favor of the King, the Advantages of that Power and Intereſt that would be put into their Hands, and their then very formidable Alliances abroad; but yet the Diſſenters ſtill looked upon them but as an handful of Men, and thought at laſt by their Numbers to prevail: and this was plainly and manifeſtly the Game that was then played on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The Regulation of Corporations by the <hi>Quo Warranto's,</hi> must be acknowledged to have had a great deal of Arbitrary in it, becauſe, as I have already hinted, it ſeemed to ſtrike at the great Fundamental of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberty, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts ſo much in the Freedom of Elections for Burgeſſes to ſerve in Parliament; and by this means, if Corporations might be disſranchis'd and renewed according to the King's Pleaſure, Parliaments might be molded according to the ſame. And there was alſo a particular Account upon which this Proceedure was very offenſive and ungrateful to great numbers of Men; and that is, that it was deſigned to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Succeſſion, without any Interruption or Excluſion to the next Heir, whoſe Religion was a Pretence with ſome, and a Reaſon of Conſcience with others, for hindering his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Crown; and this it did effectually do, there being few or none permitted to have any Power, or to make
<pb facs="tcp:106987:17"/> any Figure in this unprecedented univerſal Regulation, but ſuch as had beforehand openly declared againſt any ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and were zealous Aſſerters of the Monarchy in its old courſe of Deſcent: but it must always be owned, to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of thoſe Gentlemen, generally ſpeaking, all over the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that bating the Authority by which they acted, which the Parliament have declared to have been Arbitrary and Illegal, and the Reaſon of the Thing ſpeaks as much, yet as to their Actings themſelves, or as to their Behaviour in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Charges, they ſhewed plainly, that what they had done was only out of an honest and an upright Zeal for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Monarchy in its true Line, in oppoſition to the Practices and Deſigns of <hi>Republicans</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who were glad of any colour or ſhadow of a Reaſon, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and as they thought, to weaken it, and render it more precarious by ſo doing, without any thought of Compliance with a falſe Religion, or of ſubmitting themſelves and their Poſterity to the old Bondage of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And as one great Inſtance and aſſured Token of their Firmneſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy to the Religion eſtabliſh'd, they ſent us a Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive like themſelves, after all the Art and Induſtry uſed by Court Emiſſaries and Agents at the reſpective Elections in the beginning of the last Reign; a Parliament that could diſtinguiſh rightly betwixt God and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and was reſolved to give to each of them their due; a Parliament that oppoſed vigorouſly the Diſpenſing Power, and ſtood up firmly to the Church and the Laws; and a Parliament that, as the Right Reverend my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in one of the ſix Papers that go under his Name, obſerves, made ſufficient Amends for the Faults of their Election, by their perſonal Virtues, and by the Courage and Conſtancy which they ſhewed in the Defence of their Religion and Country: ſo that when the Point of Succeſſion was now over by the immediate Heir's
<pb facs="tcp:106987:18"/> being actually in the Throne, and when they would not break in upon thoſe Walls and Fences that had ſo long preſerved this Paradiſe of <hi>England</hi> from the Revages and Incurſions of the Boars out of the Wood, and the ſavage Beaſts of the Deſart and the Field, there was now no longer uſe of ſuch Men, they were diſcarded and diſſolved, as unfit for any future Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and new Regulations, and of another ſort, were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, in which none could be found ſo fit for the preſent Turn, as they that were formerly the most eager and clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for the Paſſing the Bill of Excluſion, the Commonwealth and the Diſſenting Party, who more out of Hatred to the Church of <hi>England</hi> than Love to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> to which they were ſtill more averſe, made large Promiſes of revoking all thoſe Teſts and other Penal Laws relating to Religion, by which the eſtabliſh'd Church was fortified and defended: and this was done, as it were, by way of Bargain between the two Parties; for the King would not annul the Penal Laws against Proteſtant Diſſenters, unleſs the Teſts and other Laws against Popiſh Recuſants, might be aboliſhed and abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated at the ſame time; and the Diſſenters, great numbers of them, for I do not, I dare not charge them all, were content, upon this Condition, to let their new Confederates, the Papiſts, enjoy the ſame Freedom and Liberty with themſelves, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after this, when they had deſtroyed the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to try what work they could make with their new Friends and Allies, which at the long run, and at the wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the bottom, was manifeſtly the Deſign of both Parties upon each other; for the nature of things will never permit there ſhould be a laſting Peace. betwixt Parties of Such different Intereſts, and of ſuch fix'd and rooted Averſions on both ſides; ſo that it must needs be plain to any Man that ſhall conſider it, that the Diſſenting and Commonwealth Party, who were generally the most hot for Paſſing the Bill
<pb facs="tcp:106987:18"/> of Excluſion, beſides the just Averſions which they had to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, had an eye at the weakning of the Monarchy it ſelf, which they thought by this means might be impaired, and that the other who were againſt it, had not the least thought of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the eſtabliſh'd Religion, but rather acted, as they then conceived, for the Defence and Preſervation of it, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and the Eſtabliſhment of the Church of <hi>England</hi> being ſo plainly bound up in each other: tho I deny not all this while, but many worthy Gentlemen acted in this Affair for the Excluding Side, out of no other Principle but a just Tenderneſs and conſcientious Regard to their Religion and Liberties, and becauſe they were of Opinion, the Monarchy was not like to run ſo great an hazard by one ſingle Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the Succeſſion to the Crown: and on the other ſide, the Non-Excluders, tho what they did was out of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Policy and State, and out of Principles of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence too; yet Time, the only true Judge of Controverſies of this nature, hath at length taught them by an Experience much to be lamented and deplored, that there may be an Exceſs of Loyalty upon ſome Occaſions, and that Princes of that Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are never to be obliged by all the utmoſt Services that can be done them, that they know no Gratitude, and can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber no Kindneſs, but look upon all as unprofitable Servants that will not be Converts, as well as they have been Friends.</p>
            <p>Now though nothing be more unskilful, if it be not unjuſt and wicked, than to tack the Avoidance of the Charters and the Regulation of the Hoſpitals ſo very cloſe together, as if they had an inſeparable Connexion with each other and were not to be parted, and to affirm, that the one being Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Illegal, the other muſt of neceſſity be ſo too; yet this is almost the only thing that is pretended against it; this is that that hath drawn ſuch an <hi>Odium</hi> upon this latter Action for the ſake of the former, that it is reckoned by all
<pb facs="tcp:106987:19"/> that have not, or cannot, or will not pry into the true ſtate of the Caſe, among the Arbitrary Tranſactions of that Reign, and the Perſons employed in the Service of theſe Houſes, in the room of any that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ejected from them, are blackned and branded by their Enemies for the ſake of their Cauſe; we will allow them, that the firſt Hint of the aforeſaid Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions was taken from the ſeizure of the City Charter into the King's Hands, and that the Charter being voided, there was a neceſſity that the Hoſpitals, which were annexed to and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into the City, ſhould be managed as the City was, by a more particular and immediate Commiſſion from the King; but yet the King need not have made any Regulation all this while; and unleſs they can prove that the King might not have viſited, though the Charter had been in full force and virtue, they do nothing at all, or at least nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for if he might not have viſited and made what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations he ſaw fit, in caſe the Charter had been ſtanding, I would fain know what is the meaning of that Clauſe in the Act of Parliament of K. <hi>Hen. 8.</hi> which I have cited, or of that Reſervation in the Grant of K. <hi>Edw. 6. ?</hi> but if he might viſit though the Charter were ſtill ſtanding, then the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legality of the Seizure or Avoidance of the Charter, could by no means affect the Regulations that were made in theſe chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Houſes, becauſe they have another and a diſtinct Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whereby to defend themſelves.</p>
            <p>Again, if the Seizure of the Charters themſelves, though it could not be juſtified by Law, and was defective and arbitrary as to the Authority upon which it proceeded; yet had ſuch a Reaſon of Equity, or of Prudence, or Neceſſity, or whatever we ſhall call it, as did really reconcile, if not recommend it too, to ſome that were no Friends to Arbitrary Power, how much more reaſonable was the Viſitation made in this and other Houſes, and the Regulations conſequent upon it, when the
<pb facs="tcp:106987:19"/> King proceeded by virtue of a Power, which even the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Adverſaries it hath must after all acknowledge to be his due; nay, what an Abſurdity would it have been for him not to viſit, where he hath ſuch an unqueſtionable Right of Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to expel thoſe Enemies of his out of his own Houſe that ſay in their Hearts, <hi>We are for a Commonwealth,</hi> and <hi>we will not have this Man to reign over us.</hi> For, turn a Diſſenter, or an Half conformiſt, or a Favourer or Abetter of ſuch, turn him forward and backward, topſy turvy, inſide and out-ſide, ſet his Face towards <hi>Samaria,</hi> or ſet it towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he is ſtill the ſame Perſon all over, in every part and in every Poſition, a Commonwealth-man, and an Enemy to Monarchy, whether he knows it or deſigns it or no; and he differs no more under one Repreſentation from what he is in another, any honeſt and fair Repreſentation I mean, than the Southern and the Eaſtern Proſpect of the ſame Building, which are all eſſential to, and conſtitutive of the whole, and are but ſeveral Parts of the ſame Aggregate or Commonwealth of Stones of which it is compiled. It is an hard Caſe that a King must be forced to accept of ſuch to be his Governors or Officers and Servants in his Houſe, that are all of them Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to his Government in their Notions, and most of them in their Deſigns; and if he be not forced to ſubmit to theſe extravagant terms, ſo that Governors of a Feather ſhall chuſe one another by conſent, and ſhall adminiſter the Affairs of the Houſe whether he will or no, and ſhall call Committees if they pleaſe, of a ſelect number, to plot against the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, under pretence of doing the Buſineſs of the Houſe; I ſay, if he be not thus forced, but may be Law diſcard either Officers or Governors at his Pleaſure, then it is plain, that they who pretend to reſtore the very Perſons that were ſo eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, do aſſume to themſelves a Diſpenſing Power in no leſs than five ſeveral Reſpects, which is enough in all Conſcience for Subjects to do.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:20"/>
            <p>Firſt, They diſpenſe, and whether the King will or no; whoſe Authority firſt gave the Sanction to the Law, with that Clauſe of the Act of King <hi>H. 8.</hi> by which the King and his Succeſſors for the time being, were for ever inveſted with a Power and Right of Viſitation and Redreſs, by rendering that Clauſe altogether fruitleſs, inſignificant and vain.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They diſpenſe with the Reſervation in the Grant of King <hi>Edward VI.</hi> by which after all his Conceſſions to the City of <hi>London,</hi> he ſtill reſerved this Power and Right to himſelf and to his Succeſſors in the Throne for ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They diſpenſe with that particular Clauſe in the ſaid Grant, whereby <hi>a fit and convenient Miniſter is</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>to celebrate Divine Services, and adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Sacramentals to the Poor and Officers, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſaid Hoſpital and Houſe;</hi> for by that <hi>fit</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient</hi> Miniſter, I have undeniably proved in my Appendix to the Queries upon the Statute of <hi>H. 8.</hi> That a Clergy-man of the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to Law was intended, and the ſame muſt be underſtood of the Officers of the Houſe, to whom the ſaid Hoſpitaller cannot otherwiſe adminiſter the Sacraments and Sacramentals, nor celebrate Divine Services in their preſence and hearing, as King <hi>Edward</hi> required they ſhould do; but as for the Poor indeed it is another Caſe, there is an occaſional Diſpenſation certainly included in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing, for it does by no means follow, becauſe a Man cannot bring himſelf to be of our Perſuaſion, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Neceſſities muſt not be relieved, his Wants ſupplied, or his Diſeaſes, Wounds, or Ailments cured, but for Officers and Servants there is no color of excuſe in ſo great Choice of fit Perſons to be found; and if not Officers of a Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party, then it follows plainly, nor Governors neither, becauſe ſuch Governors will always abuſe their Truſt in favor of that Intereſt and party to which they belong, and they will think themſelves bound to contravene and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb facs="tcp:106987:20"/> this Proviſion of King <hi>Edward</hi> even for Conſcience ſake, to propagate and encourage that which they eſteem the only true Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and to diſcourage that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality and Superſtition of ours, which they ſo loudly and ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately, and in their own Thoughts ſo deſervedly complain of; nay, if we add Experience to Reaſon and conjecture, we know by long Experience, that they have always acted according to theſe meaſures.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They diſpenſe with the qualifying Act of the <hi>25 Car. 2.</hi> as I have proved ſufficiently in the following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, it is Sir <hi>Edward Hales</hi> his Caſe, the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford's</hi> Caſe, the <hi>Charter Houſe</hi> Caſe, and the whole <hi>Magdalen Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> Caſe, as exactly as any thing can be, only with this Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which makes it ſo much the worſe, that it is a Power exerciſed by Subjects, not by Kings, by Subjects in contempt of the juſt Power and Prerogative of their Prince, by Subjects in derogation to the ſtanding Laws of the Realm, and in defiance both of King and Parliament together.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, They diſpenſe with the late Act for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing the Judgment in a <hi>quo Warranto, &amp;c.</hi> for by that Act, or I am much miſtaken, after having very ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it, the preſent Lord Mayor, commonly ſo call'd, and ſeveral of his Collegues and Aſſeſſors upon the Bench are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared not to be, and never to have been legal and rightful Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City ſo that the Governors and Officers pretending to be reſtored, holding by no other Authority but theirs, and there not being a Majority in that Court without them: There is nothing more certain than that they hold by nothing, which is hardly ſo good as a drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man by a Reed, and yet he muſt drown for all that.</p>
            <p>For my part, I muſt be frank and clear with your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and the World, that it ſeems to me a great Scandal to the Government, it caſts a Blemiſh of Diſhonor, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Weakneſs and Infirmity upon the Supreme Power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:106987:21"/> when its Enemies, ſuch as are at leaſt virtually and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentally, if not actually ſo, ſhall be ſuffered to ſwagger and domineer, with the bluſtring Title of <hi>Governors,</hi> to which they have no Title, though they behave themſelves of all Men the moſt imperiouſly and proudly under the lofty Imaginations that it puts into their weak Heads, in a place where the King hath a legal and rightful Viſitation, and it is a further diſhonor in this Caſe, where they can make out no Title to ſo proud a Word, that his Friends and Servants ſhall be affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and curb'd, after having had the Improvements of a polite and liberal Education, by every little thing that hath neither Parts nor Breeding, merely becauſe it preſumes to call it ſelf a Governor, though it knows not how to govern it ſelf, and is hardly qualified to be Governor of <hi>Jack Strawe</hi>'s Caſtle, but yet is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as full and as big ſwell'd with the title, as if it were indeed the Governor of ſome mighty Fortreſs, that had a powerful Gariſon at its Devotion, and the Country for twenty or thirty Miles round under Military Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if the King of the Country, by whoſe only Power and Authority he acts, ſhould pretend to viſit or call him to an account; he could immediately ſet him and his Army under Water, and ſo farewell to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, for all are <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to the Diſſenters and Commonwealths-men but themſelves, they are the only true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when all is done, and they make no bones of ſtealing this Crown Jewel of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to viſit from an <hi>Aegyptian</hi> King, or indeed any King whatſoever, for no King comes amiſs, they love them all and their Prerogative ſo well.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I do humbly propoſe it to your Lordſhip's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that it is not only a diſhonor to their Majeſties, that any of their Charities ſhould be wholly managed by Men of a Republican Principle and Party, but that the Peace of this Houſecan never be ſecured, unleſs we be all of a Mind, as well the Governors as the Officers and Servants, true and
<pb facs="tcp:106987:21"/> hearty Communicants of the Eſtabliſh'd Church, and ſuch as have given ſuch proofs of Conformity and Steadineſs to the Government both in Church and State, as the Law requires; then, and not before, it is that we may expect to ſee happy Days, if it be poſſible in a miſerable Place, and in the midſt of Sickneſs and Diſeaſes; not till then it is that the Affairs of this Houſe, diſturbed by mutual Animoſities and inteſtine Broils, will go on with an even and ſucceſsful Pace, to the Credit of the Government, and to the utmoſt Advantage of the Sick and Wounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> I humbly beg your Lordſhip's Pardon for this very long, this unexpectedly long preliminary Addreſs; I ſhall add but two things more, and that very briefly, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. My Lord, What are theſe Gentlemen that will needs make themſelves Parties, and will needs be Defendants in this Cauſe against us? The Plaintiffs certainly know beſt who it is by whom they are aggrieved, and they complain of none but of Sir <hi>T. P.</hi> the pretended Lord Mayor, and thoſe of his Brethren that have concurred with him for the diſplacing of thoſe whom K. <hi>Charles II.</hi> by an undoubted Prerogative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in the Crown ſent hither, and for the reſtoring of thoſe whom he by the ſame Right hath ejected. I have nothing to ſay to <hi>Hughes,</hi> as to the Money that hath been paid him; but I must expect my Satisfaction from thoſe by whoſe Order it was done; and they, if any, are the Defendants in this Cauſe. And here there are two Points to be inſiſted upon: firſt, Whether the Court of Aldermen, at the paſſing of thoſe Orders, were a legal Court? or, Whether it be ſo or no to this very day, till it be purged of thoſe that have nothing to do to ſit there, and till the Number be filled up by thoſe that are better qualified to take the Stile and Dignity of Aldermen upon them? Secondly, The King's Power of Viſitation being
<pb facs="tcp:106987:22"/> acknowledged, as we are ready to prove it undeniably, if it be diſputed, whether even a legal Court of Aldermen can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcind the legal Act of the King, in an Affair that lies ſo plainly and ſo properly within his Royal Cognizance and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation. But as for theſe Gentlemen that call themſelves Governors, and will by all means be Parties under that Name and Notion, who are they? Are they not all, or the much greatest part of them, the very ſame Men that were ejected by K. <hi>Charles II.?</hi> ſo that their Title to the Stile and Office of Governors of this Houſe, is a thing every whit as much diſputed, and for the ſame Reaſon, as that of any of the Officers pretending to be reſtored? How then comes it to paſs, that they ſo confidently preſume to act as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates or Attorneys of this Houſe, and to appear before Your Lordſhip as a Repreſentative of the whole Body of Governors in its behalf, when yet all this while it is a very great Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether they do really belong to it or no, and a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that cannot be reſolved in their Favour, as I humbly conceive, without the Admiſſion of a Diſpenſing Power in Men that never pretended to it till now, and that decry it in Princes themſelves. But they appear in the Hoſpital Behalf, and they were to be commended for their Charity to appear in the Behalf of a charitable Foundation, to reſcue it from Abuſes, and to aſſert its Rights, if they did all this at their own Charge; but it is their Majeſties and the Hoſpital that muſt pay for all this out of the Hoſpital Stock, though the Deſign be nothing elſe but to overthrow the Royal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and to clip the Wings of the Imperial Eagles: but this is the Commonwealth Notion of the Liberty of the Subject, the Deſtruction of the Rights and Prerogatives of Kings.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, my Lord, as the beſt refuge which our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries have in a very ſhameleſs and defenceleſs Cauſe, they are pleaſed to ſay, that our Orders from the Commiſſion run
<pb facs="tcp:106987:22"/> only <hi>during pleaſure,</hi> and that that pleaſure and its effects are extinct, the one of which we grant, the other we deny, for the pleaſure of that Court was the pleaſure of the King, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dyes, though he may recal what he hath done by a new Commiſſion or by a new and further Declaration of his own will, but for an inferior Court, whoſe Abuſes were intended to be corrected, to renew and act over again the ſame Abuſes, and to reſtore the very ſame Perſons and Powers that were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded, upon pretence that the pleaſure of the Commiſſion, which they never withdrew by any act of theirs is extinct by their Diſſolution, is to render the King's Power of Viſitation, a thing ſo extremely mean, little and contemtible, and beſides to caſt a Blemiſh either of Ignorance, or which is a greater diſhonor, of injuſtice upon him that it is plea not to be endured; and I am ſure it ſcarce deſerves an Anſwer. If the Governors had choſen an Officer upon a Competition, and and the odds had been thirty and thirty one, or any other number making only one difference; it is certain it he odds had carried it; but ſuppoſe within a day or two, two of the thirty one had died or reſigned their Staves as Governors of the Houſe or in this Caſe it is certain, that the pleaſure of the thirty one, had been extinct, in the ſame Senſe that that of the Commiſſioners is pretended to be, and then the Will of the thirty ſtill ſuppoſed to be ſurviving muſt have prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Officer choſen by the thirty one, ejected to make room for him that was choſen by the thirty, which is flat and clean contrary to the Courſe and Practice of all Elections, and is a ſufficient Idication, that the Legality of ſuch Acts when they are done, derives a Validity upon them, even in Arbitrary Dependences ſor the time to come, unleſs they be repealed by a ſuperior or at leaſt an equal Authority, and the nature of Juſtice and Morality require that it ſhould be done likewiſe for equitable Reaſons; and if
<pb facs="tcp:106987:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Act of Parliament for the reverſing the Judgment, hath confirm'd all thoſe Acts during the avoidance of the Charter, which would have been legal, had the Charter ſtood, how much more might thoſe Acts to be eſteem'd valid, which have alſo a legal Foundation, as this Commiſſion manifeſtly had, ſo far as the Hoſpitals were concern'd, whether the Charter had been ſeized or no?</p>
            <p>My Lord, It is rather the King and Queen are the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs in this Cauſe than we, it is their Eternal Prerogaiive, more than our Temporary Intereſt that is concerned, and it is plainly a Conteſt and a Struggle betwixt a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth-Faction, and the Monarchy and Crown of <hi>England.</hi> I ſhall detain your Lordſhip no longer from the peruſal of the following <hi>Memorial,</hi> but humbly beg leave to write and ſubſcribe my ſelf, My Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Servant, John Turner.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 25. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106987:23"/>
            <head>A MEMORIAL Humbly Preſented to the Right Honorable The Lord Chief Juſtice OF THE <hi>KING'S-BENCH,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it Pleaſe Your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Caſe referred to your Lordſhip by the Council-Board is ſo plain, that it needs only opening and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet in its true Light to determine that Juſtice, which is byaſs'd by nothing but Reaſons drawn from it ſelf, to the Plaintiff's ſide.</p>
            <p>My Lord, By a Clauſe in a Statute of the <hi>28th. H. 8. c.</hi> 21. it is provided, <hi>That it ſhall not be lawful for the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>or any other Perſon or Perſons to viſit or vex any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hoſpitals, Houſes, or other places Religious, which be or were exempt before the making of this Act, but that Redreſs, Viſitation and Confirmation, ſhall be had by the King's Highneſs by Commiſſion under the Great Seal, to be directed to ſuch Perſons as ſhall be appointed requiſite for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Royal Grant of King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. to the Mayor, Commonalty, and Citizens of the City, of <hi>London,</hi> whereby the ordinary Government and Adminiſtration of the ſaid <hi>Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106987:24"/> and its Lands, Revenues, and Poſſeſſions is entirely committed to and entruſted with the Mayor, Commonalty, and Citizens aforeſaid; yet there is ſtill notwithſtanding a ſpecial Proviſo in extraordinary Caſes, whereby the Power of Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Regulation in the ſaid <hi>Hoſpital</hi> is reſerved to the King and his Succeſſors for ever; the very Words of the Clauſe are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And We will and declare by theſe Preſents, that it ſhall be lawful for Us, Our Heirs and Succeſſors from time to time, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as it ſhall ſeem fit and expedient, to aſſign Our Commiſſioners to viſit the ſaid</hi> Hoſpital <hi>and</hi> Houſe <hi>of the</hi> Poor, <hi>and to do and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all and ſingular ſuch other things whatſoever, as We, Our Heirs and Succeſſors ſhall there command to be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Clauſe in the Act of Parliament, which is ſtill in force, that Act having never yet been repealed either in whole or in part; it is plain, that if this <hi>Hoſpital</hi> were ſuch, though it were not an <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of the ſame nature, before the making of this Act, if it were a Religious Houſe, in the ſame ſenſe that all Charitable Foundations are interpreted to be ſo; and if it were a Place exempt from Epiſcopal Juriſdiction at the time of the making of this Act and before it, and hath continued ſo ever ſince, in virtue of that ancient Exemption, which it is matter of Fact that it hath done, and it is equally certain, that it can plead no other Right of Exemption, but this to this very day, then is it without controverſie a Place ſubject to the King's Viſitation by virtue of this Act, and that the Kings and Queens of <hi>England</hi> for the time being, may, for ever viſit and regulate all Abuſes and Miſgovernments from time to time that ſhall or may ariſe, or ſhall be by them deemed or adjudged to ariſe in the Adminiſtration or Superintendency of the ſame.</p>
            <p>As to the Clauſe produced and cited out of the Grant of King <hi>Edward,</hi> whereby he reſerves a Power of Viſitation to himſelf and Succeſſors for ever in the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark,</hi> which is the Scene of the Controverſie now depending before your Lordſhip, it hath two ſeveral Foundations to rely upon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Clauſe that hath been alledged out of the Act of <hi>H.</hi> 8. by which he was intruſted with a Power of Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all Religious Houſes and Places exempt as this is; and Parliamentary Truſts ratified and accepted by the Royal San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106987:24"/> can no more be violated than Coronation Oaths; for every Law is a part of the matter of that Oath, which oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the King equally to obſerve and maintain all the Laws, and in every Truſt lodged in the King by Act of Parliament; the Performance of it is ſuppoſed to be exacted and called for by the ſame Authority, which is always ſitting, always in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing until that fiduciary Conſtitution be repealed. So that King <hi>Edward,</hi> though he had not reſerved to himſelf a Power of Viſitation in this and other ſuch Places, yet the Act it ſelf would have obliged him and his Succeſſors to viſit, as often as occaſion ſhould require, neither could he ſo entirely devolve ſuch a Truſt as this upon the Mayor, Commonalty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London,</hi> or upon any other Perſon or Perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as totally to neglect and abandon it himſelf, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies not only a Power of viſiting at all times, but a neceſſity of doing it in ſome particular Caſes, to conſent that another ſhall betray that Truſt which is committed to me, or to put it wholly out of my power to call him to account for his Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Male-Adminſtration of it, being the ſame thing in the iſſue and Concluſion, though it go ſomewhat further about, as if I had actually and willfully betrayed it in my own Perſon. If the words had been never ſo expreſs, never ſo abſolute, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt ſhadow of any reſerve or exception, by which this <hi>Hoſpital</hi> was conſigned over to the Commonalty and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>London:</hi> Yet ſtill the King's Power of Viſitation had been ſuppoſed, becauſe he could not give away the Act of Parliament, nor any Prerogative inherent in the Crown to the diminution of his own rightful Power, or that of his Heirs and Succeſſors in after times, and eſpecially in ſuch a Caſe as this, where not only a Power was lodged, but a Truſt for the good of others was repoſed in him, by the Repreſentative Body of the Nation, which includes and draws after it the diffuſive, and all this with his own Royal Aſſent, which though he may give, or not give before the Sanction, yet after it he cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it as he pleaſeth; which would be to give him a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power in the utmoſt Latitude and Comprehenſion of it, againſt the true Meaning and Intention of all Laws, which always deſign to be obſerved and obeyed, as well by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as others, ſo far as he hath put himſelf under the Force and Obligation of them.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106987:25"/>
            <p>This is the firſt Ground, upon which the Reſervation in the Grant of King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. to the Mayor and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London</hi> relies; it is an Act of Parliament made in his Father's time, by which he was not only impowered to viſit all exempt Places, but it was left with him and his Succeſſors in Truſt, and is a Charge which he was bound to look after, as often as any real, or to him ſo ſeeming Neceſſity ſhould require.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Ground that juſtifies and warrants the Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is taken from the nature of the Gift it ſelf; every Man that gives or bequeaths any thing to a publick Uſe muſt be allowed to do it upon his own Conditions, and with his own Reſervations, ſuppoſing them to be reaſonable or poſſible in themſelves. Without an Act of Parliament any private Donor, may appoint, if he ſo pleaſeth, certain extraordinary Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to inſpect and examine, as occaſion ſhall require, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the ordinary Truſtees, and much more then may a King do the ſame, when he hath an Act of Parliament to authorize and defend him in it, in a publick Charity of his own Foundation.</p>
            <p>In virtue of this double Authority, and this double Truſt derived to him from the Act of Parliament, and from the Grant of King <hi>Edward,</hi> his late Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> II. did viſit the Royal <hi>Hoſpitals,</hi> belonging to this City, by his Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers under the Broad Seal, as the Act of Parliament required he ſhould do; and in this Viſitation he diſplaced ſeveral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and ſeveral Governors too, and placed others in their ſtead.</p>
            <p>Which things being premiſed in order to the more clear and faithful Repreſentation of our Caſe; We preſume with all humble Submiſſion to your Lordſhip, that as to the Viſitation in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral conſidered, there can be no queſtion, as to the Legality of it, it being done in purſuance of a very reaſonable and juſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Grant, and by Commiſſioners under the Broad-Seal of <hi>England,</hi> as the Act of Parliament required, all the queſtion is, whether there were at that time any juſt Ground, any reaſonable or ſufficient Cauſe of Viſitation or no, and this, my Lord, is a Queſtion capable of a two-fold Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106987:25"/>
            <p>Firſt, The King is not bound to give an Account of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why he viſits. And Secondly, If he were bound, the Reaſons were notorious, and ſuch as in the Judgment of any indifferent Perſon might abundantly juſtifie a Royal Viſitation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The King is not bound to give an Account of the Reaſons why he viſits, or for the Regulations which he makes as to Officers and Servants belonging to the Houſe, in any ſuch Viſitation.</p>
            <p>Indeed if the King ſhould go about to alter the Conſtitution, to imbezzle the Charity, or to convert it to a quite different Uſe; this would be ſo plain an Abuſe of his Power and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his Truſt, as would ſufficiently warrant the Mayor and Commonalty and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> or any others in whom the ordinary Truſt and Management was lodged to ſtand it out againſt him, and to vindicate their Title by a courſe of Law, by which the true Meaning and Intention of the Donor would appear from the expreſs words of the Grant, which it would always be eaſie to produce, and the King, who by the ſaid Grant was made and conſtituted the Supreme Guardian and Viſitor of the Charity beſtowed therein, could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with any color or pretence of Right either imbezzle, ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and abuſe it to no good Uſe at all, or convert it to any other Uſe than what the Founder himſelf had allotted.</p>
            <p>But for the Officers and Servants it is another Caſe, if the King be bound to give a particular Account, why he turns out ſuch and puts others in their room, then he ſhall not viſit at all, he ſhall have no Power either to put in or out, even though never ſo great Abuſes be committed, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the ordinary Truſtees; and till they ſhall approve of the Reaſons of his ſo doing, which is effectually to take the power of Viſitation out of his Hands, and to make the Act of Parliament and the Reſervation in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Grant, both of them very vain and inſignificant things.</p>
            <p>Beſides, It is an Opinion which the moſt Eminent and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lawyers of this Nation have owned and eſpouſed under there reſpective Hands, and which we are ready to produce, that the Officers and Servants of St. <hi>Thomas Hoſpital</hi> are not Charter-Officers, but Servants ef ſuch a nature, that they may be turned out or put in at pleaſure by the Court of Aldermen,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106987:26"/> or the Governors acting under them, even without a Reaſon, as Maſters of Families may do with their hired Servants, or Shop-keepers with their Journeymen, or Merchants with their Factors, with whom they have not contracted for any length of time, but may keep them in their Service or diſmiſs them from it, as they pleaſe themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now if this be the Power of the ordinary Governors and Truſtees themſelves, then the King who hath always a Power and Right of Viſitation, Paramount and Superior to any that they can pretend to, may much more do the ſame, and cannot be accountable to any for ſo doing, any more than, nor indeed ſo much as the ordinary Feoffees, becauſe he acts by an Authority Superior to theirs, and becauſe the laſt Appeal, beyond which there is no remedy, is lodged in him.</p>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe, if your Lordſhip pleaſeth, what hath already been unqueſtionably proved, that the King in this buſineſs acted not only by virtue of that highly rational and prudent Truſt that was repoſed in him by the Grant of King <hi>Edward,</hi> but alſo by virtue of that very Power which was given him by an Act of Parliament never yet repealed either in whole or in part.</p>
            <p>In this Caſe, my Lord, with your Lordſhip's good leave, it is very plain, that when upon a Viſitation, the King diſplaceth ſome Officers and placeth others in their ſtead; if upon the diſſolution of the Commiſſion, which may be done the next moment after the Regulation is made, the ordinary Truſtees ſhall be inveſted with a power of turning the Tables upon him, of putting out thoſe whom he put in, and putting in thoſe whom he put out, which is our preſent Caſe, and it is that wherein the chief Pinch of the Controverſie lies, then this Proviſion in the Act of Parliament is altogether vain; the King's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is rendred uſeleſs and contemptible, and the Lord May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London</hi> are effectually fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with a Diſpenſing Power: For he or they that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence with one Statute, may do the ſame by another, and in Conſequence by all, they being only ſo many ſeveral Exerciſes of one and the ſame abſolute and uncontrolable Right; ſo that this is not only to ſubmit to a Power which we pretend to diſclaim, but it is to take the Scepter out of the King's Hands
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106987:26"/> and to put it into thoſe of the City, to change the Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from a Monarchy to a Commonwealth, or rather to make the Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, to be the King of <hi>England</hi> in the moſt abſolute and arbitrary Senſe. For <hi>diſpenſare, boc eſt, lege ſolvere is ſolus poteſt qui ferendae abrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeque legis poteſtatem habet,</hi> they are the words of <hi>Grotius,</hi> he only can diſpenſe with a Law that hath a Power of making or annull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and the ſame is the Opinion of <hi>Vaſquez, Suarez, Pufendorf,</hi> and others, and of that Right Reverend and Learned Author himſelf, by whom theſe Opinions are collected and ſet down in his admirable Diſcourſe concerning the illegality of the late Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Commiſſion, <hi>p. 33.</hi> And my Lord Chief Baron <hi>Atkins</hi> in his accurate Enquiry into the Power of Diſpenſing with Penal Statutes, <hi>p.</hi> 23, 24 endeavors to prove by ſeveral Inſtances of temporary Diſpenſations with the Statute of Proviſors, and other Statutes, <hi>That the Power of Diſpenſing with Acts of Parliament is no where elſe but where the Legiſlative Power is, and that the Kings (of</hi> England) <hi>have ſometimes accepted it from them in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſes, and for ſome limited time, and with divers Reſtrictions, which is a full acknowledgment,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that it belongs only to the Legiſlative Power to diſpenſe with Laws.</hi> And this, my Lord, is plainly the Reaſon of the thing, for every Law includes an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, otherwiſe it is no Law becauſe it does not bind, and no Obligation can be taken off, but by a Power either equal or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to that which made it. Now if the Lord Mayor and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London,</hi> may not only eject out of the Royal Hoſpitals thoſe whom the King hath placed there, but alſo reſtore thoſe very Men whom he hath diſcarded, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Act of Parliament gives him a Power without Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to viſit and redreſs, that is, it gives him the ſame power, over the Officers of ſuch Houſes, that Maſters of Families have over their Domeſticks, who may keep their Servants or turn them out of doors without giving a Reaſon; then is that very Diſpenſing Power admitted and allowed in the Corporation of <hi>London,</hi> which is deny'd to the King; and in this particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance they do not only barely contend with the Law, but they juſtle the King out of his undoubted Prerogative, and unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Right, and bring both Him and the Parliament under
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106987:27"/> their Girdle, ſo that, <hi>Now thoſe eminent Promiſes do haſten to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment,</hi> as a late Author expreſſes it, in a Sermon printed to juſtifie and affirm the execrable Murther of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>For binding of Kings in chains and Nobles with fetters of Iron;</hi> for diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying of Kings and Parliaments together; <hi>ſuch honor have all his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, my Lord, you are always of Council for the King ſo far at leaſt as not to ſuffer his Prerogative Royal to be unjuſtly inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and therefore we reſt aſſured that your Lordſhip will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine nothing, as well for that Reaſon, as out of a wiſe and honorable Senſe of the great Equity and Juſtice of our Cauſe, that ſhall in its Conſequence affect the Government, as it is now happily Eſtabliſh'd, or in any wiſe tend to the diminution of their Majeſties juſt and clear Prerogative, or to the Diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Imperial Crown of this Realm, and that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will remember that the Declaration of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which was preſented to their preſent Majeſties, the then Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> and which in every part of it hath been ſince confirmed by an Act of Parliament, Entituled, <hi>An Act declaring the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and ſettling the Succeſſion of the Crown.</hi> Which ſaid Declaration and Act thereupon enſuing have pronounced all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending of Laws, and all diſpenſing with them without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Parliament to be illegal: I ſay, I know your Lordſhip will conſider that the ſame Authority that deny'd this Power of Diſpenſing to the King and Queen themſelves, upon Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Miſchiefs and Calamities it produced in the late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Reign, would much leſs have granted the ſame extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, inordinate and inconvenient Privilege to Subjects; nay, they would never have thought of it without Indignation and Scorn, and I leave it with your Lordſhip to determine as you ſhall ſee cauſe, whether the Mayor and Commonalty of <hi>London</hi>'s reſtoring thoſe to their reſpective Places, whom the King hath legally ejected, by virtue of a Clauſe in an expreſs Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, veſting him with ſuch a Right, be not a plain Inſtance of a Diſpenſing Power, by rendering this Clauſe altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant and uſeleſs, and whether it be not ſo much the more criminal for being exerciſed not by the King, but by Subjects,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106987:27"/> and thoſe not of the firſt Rank and Quality neither, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt both of King and Parliament together?</p>
            <p>And, my Lord, I beg leave to propound this further Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your Lordſhip, whether the Reſtitution of the ejected Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers by the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, do deſtroy and evacuate the King's Right of Viſitation or no? For upon Suppoſition that it doth, they are not only furniſht with a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſuſpending Laws, and of diſpenſing with them, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of abrogating, reſcinding and repealing them too, which is to make them every whit as abſolute, as the moſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, enlarged, and unconfined notion of Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf can be. If it doth not, then as they immediately upon the Diſſolution of the Commiſſion, which as I have ſaid, may be done the next moment after the Regulation is made, as they may immediately reſtore thoſe whom the King hath eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſo may the King the very next minute by a new Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eject thoſe whom they have reſtored; and thus there will be a circle of Appeals, and Controverſies will be endleſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion unavoidable, as long as ſuch a changeable and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain State of things ſhall continue: it is therefore humbly left to your Lordſhip, whether you think it more reaſonable to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine for the King and Queen, and for the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who have given them this power of viſiting and redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as they ſhall find cauſe, or for a few miſtaken Men, who, whatever right of Government in ordinary caſes they have, yet have none at all in Derogation to the King's Prerogative, and in Oppoſition to ſuch a particular and ſpecial Viſitation as is by this Act of Parliament provided for.</p>
            <p>All this hath been ſaid, may it pleaſe your Lordſhip, upon occaſion of the firſt Head propoſed to be inſiſted upon, that the King is not bound to give an Account of the Reaſons why he viſits, and that tho the Ejectment of the Gentlemen concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed had been never ſo Arbitrary, yet it is good in Law; the Law gives the King an Arbitrary and Deſpotical Power in theſe Caſes, ſo he do not ſubſtitute in the room of thoſe ejected, ſuch other Perſons as are not duly qualified by Law, or are otherwiſe groſly and notoriouſly incapable of their reſpective Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and this, I hope, it hath been ſufficiently proved that he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106987:28"/> may do, to call him to a ſtrict Account for the Reaſons and Cauſes of his Viſitation, beſides that the Act of Parliament is general and without any reſerve, being in effect to take the power of Viſitation out of his Hands, for he that cannot viſit but when others pleaſe, hath no power or right of Viſitation that is properly his own.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond thing to be inſiſted upon, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the King were accountable for what he did, as in very truth he is not, yet that there are ſufficient Reaſons to be given.</p>
            <p>My Lord, The order of Council referring the Conſideration of this Matter to your Lordſhip, ſets forth as a part of the Matter of our Petition, that they that claim againſt us were ejected by his late Majeſty for not being legally qualified, and ſo they undoubtedly were, if the Act of Parliament of the <hi>25th</hi> of that King for preventing of Dangers which may happen from Popiſh Recuſants were a good Law, and were then in full force and virtue; for by that Act it is expreſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd, <hi>That all that receive any Salary, Fee, or Wages, by reaſon of any Patent or Grant from his Majeſty, or ſhall have Command or Place of Truſt, from or under his Majeſty, or from any of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Predeceſſors, or by his or their Authority, or by Authority deriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him or them,</hi> ſhall undergo the Teſts, and make the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions therein mentioned, which it is needleſs to recite, they are ſo well known to all that are here preſent. Now, my Lord, our Salaries are paid us by virtue of a Grant from their Majeſties Royal Predeceſſor King <hi>Edward</hi> VI and by Authority derived from him, as all other Affairs and Matters relating to the Houſe are tranſacted by and under the Influence of the ſame Royal Grant, and by Authority derived from it: Nothing therefore can be more plain than that the Officers of this Houſe receiving Wages and Salaries from the King, or at leaſt from his Royal Predeceſſor King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and by Authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him, were obliged by the plain and expreſs Letter of that Act without any remote Conſequences or far-fetch'd Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations to undergo the Teſts and Tryals of Proteſtancy and Loyalty therein enjoin'd. But if a Diſſenter cannot take the Oath of Supremacy, which was then enjoin'd, nor receive the Sacrament according to the manner and uſage of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then by this Act he is precluded from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106987:28"/> receiving any Wages or Salary from the King or from any of his Royal Predeceſſors, or by his or their Authority, or by Authority derived from him or them; and this upon Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation will be found to have been the Caſe of moſt, if not all of thoſe, that were at that time ejected, and if any Man did comply to ſerve a turn, with theſe Teſts, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell that any one Man did, continuing ſtill a Diſſenter, and a Separatiſt from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or an half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced Conformiſt, and a frequenter of both Communions, as if it were indifferent to him what Religion he was of, as ſome ſuch there have been; yet this did by no means come up to the Intention of that Act, which the better to diſcourage and diſappoint all Popiſh Deſigns, would allow the King to truſt or reward none for any Service in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, but ſuch as were hearty and entire Conformiſts to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, all Places within the King's Viſitation are by a very natural and eaſie Interpretation within the King's Pay, for the King is ſuppoſed to employ thoſe whom he may eject out of their Employments when he pleaſeth, and to pay thoſe whoſe Salaries he may ſtop, as well without as with a Reaſon; it is clear therefore upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count alſo, That theſe are all Places within the meaning of the Act, and that there was very good Reaſon for ejecting thoſe Officers who had not qualified themſelves according as that Act required.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, my Lord, they do not only receive Wages and Salaries from the King, but there is a Truſt and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand committed to them, a Truſt as to the Adminiſtration of their reſpective Employments, and an Authority for the Execution of that Truſt; for in vain is a Truſt committed to any Man whatſoever, who is deſtitute of Power to ſee to its Execution: they are the very words of the Act, <hi>Or ſhall have Command or place of Truſt from his Majeſty, or from any of his Majeſties Predeceſſors, &amp;c.</hi> Which words <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> according to their true import and meaning, muſt be underſtood in their utmoſt Latitude and Extent of Signification, unleſs there were ſome other paſſages in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106987:29"/> Act it ſelf, that laid a particular Reſtraint and Circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption upon them. It is but a very ſmall <hi>Command</hi> and place of <hi>Truſt,</hi> which an Inferior Officer in the Exciſe or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms is poſſeſſed of; ſuppoſe a Gauger in the Exciſe, or a Land or Tide-waiter in the Cuſtoms, and even Offices in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to theſe; and yet theſe being all of them in the King's Pay have been interpreted to come within the meaning of this Act, and we know what Artifice and what Force was uſed in a late unfortunate Reign, to make them renounce their Obligation to the Teſt, and promiſe to concur to its repeal; and yet theſe have no Patent or Grant from the King, only they depend upon his verbal appointment, or they are choſen without the King's immediate privity or knowledge by their Superior Officer, and by him or them without any further to do upon any real or pretended Miſdemeanor they are diſcarded; but they receive the King's Pay for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Employments, and from this it is that the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Teſt ariſeth; and this, if it do not equally, or rather more concern all thoſe that act in the Hoſpital of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark,</hi> under the Grant or Letters Patent of King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and are paid by an Authority derived from them: Then I muſt confeſs to your Lordſhip and the World, that I have conſidered of theſe things a great while, and with a great deal of Seriouſneſs, and with an earneſt Deſire to find out and diſcover the Truth to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Act ſpeaks not only of Places of Advantage with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary or Perquiſites, or both belonging to them, but in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of all Truſts repoſed by the King, that no Perſon ought to be admitted into ſuch, but thoſe that will perform the Conditions by this Act required, and this concerns the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors as well as the Officers and Servants of the Houſe, for they are truſted, though they are not paid. I preſume it will be granted on all hands, that a known and open Papiſt ought not to be a Governor in ſuch an Houſe as this, and why then ſhould a concealed one be allowed, who is certainly much the more dangerous of the two? and how ſhall we know what any Man is in this Caſe, unleſs he perform thoſe Conditions, and undergo thoſe Teſts, without which the Law
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106987:29"/> is not ſatisfied, but he is a Popiſh Recuſant? It appears there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as evident as Demonſtration it ſelf can make it, that though the King might have ejected either Officers or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors without giving a Reaſon, or without being account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to any for what he did in this Caſe, yet that what he did was founded upon Reaſons the moſt agreeable to Law and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the moſt conducible to the Publick Good of any that could have been thought of or ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe provided by a Clauſe in the ſame Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, That any Perſon who by neglect or refuſal to do as the Act requires, ſhall loſe or forfeit any Office, and ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards qualifie himſelf by conforming to the Law, yet he ſhall not be reſtored to the Prejudice of any Perſon, who upon the Lapſe or Forfeiture, came into the Poſſeſſion of his Vacant Place, having qualified himſelf within the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix'd, as the Law requires; ſo that what firmer Tenure there can be than ours is, I cannot imagine.</p>
            <p>It cannot be thought an Injury or a piece of Perſecution, when a Man enjoys the liberty of his Conſcience, his Perſon, his Eſtate, when he is allowed all the juſt and convenient free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Converſation, together with an undiſturbed Licenſe of Traffick and Commerce, for him to be ſhut out of Places of Profit or Truſt in the diſpoſal of the State, in which he is like to be troubleſom to the Religion Eſtabliſh'd, and to the Peace of his Country; it being ſeen by Experience, that all Men in power do naturally uſe it, and for the moſt part with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable warmth and heat for the Intereſt of that particular Perſuaſion, which they themſelves have eſpouſed. The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Inconvenience of it in this Houſe appeared, in that when the Diſſenting Party had the aſcendent in it, they choſe no Officers but ſuch as were like themſelves, and the Chappel it ſelf, which is the King's Chappel, and immediately ſubject to his Royal Viſitation, was made an illegal Conventicle for three Years together, to his great diſhonor, and to the Reproach and Scandal of the Government it ſelf, and for the merit of this among other things, that do highly recommend him to that ſort of Men it is, that my Competitor, contrary to all Law and Juſtice, is abetted in his unrighteous and unreaſonable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions againſt me.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106987:30"/>
            <p>My Lord, I am not for any Man's being moleſted or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for his Conſcience ſake in Matters of mere Opinion; it is not only againſt my Judgment, but my Temper too; and indeed unleſs the neceſſity of the Publick may excuſe it, it is a Cruelty, that can never be excuſed, and for that reaſon ought never to be practiſed. I am very well pleaſed and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the Toleration which the Parliament have grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, always provided, That the Tolerated Parties be kept out of all Places and Truſts that are of a publick nature, and in the gift and diſpoſal of the State.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> is that Party of Men, which all Parties will acknowledge they can live moſt happily under, unleſs they be the Regnant Party themſelves; and we have ſeen ſo much of the inhuman Cruelties, and more than Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooning Barbarities of a Diſſenting Zeal, and ſuch unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Confuſions conſequent upon it, that the beſt and wiſeſt of the Diſſenters themſelves, though upon a Religious account, they could not ſubmit themſelves to the Epiſcopal Government, or comply with the Liturgy and Ceremonies of our Church, yet upon political Reaſons they have always declared for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting the Eſtabliſhment, as the only means to preſerve the Peace and Tranquillity of their Country, and to make us as happy and as great a People, as in our divided Circumſtances we can be: But if the Reign of thoſe that are Diſſenters from our Church be attended with ſo many miſchiefs, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a mixture of ſuch in Places of Truſt and Profit, of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or of Power in the State muſt have its proportionable Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences attending it; and for this reaſon it is, that in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> where the greateſt liberty of Religion is allowed, yet none are paid, none are truſted in any publick Employment by the States, but ſuch as are of the Eſtabliſh'd Religion: this is largely repreſented by Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> in his excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and the Reaſons of it with very great Judgment and Wiſdom are aſſigned by the <hi>Heer Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> late Pantionary of <hi>Holland</hi> in his famous Letter to Mr. <hi>James Stewart,</hi> giving an Account of the Sentiments of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties concerning the Repeal of the Teſt and the Penal Laws ſo much talk'd of and endeavor'd in the late King's time.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106987:30"/>
            <p>My Lord, I wiſh with all my Heart, for the ſake of our very Adverſaries themſelves, that nothing elſe could be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt them or any of them, as the Cauſes of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. his Viſitation, and their Ejectment conſequent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, but that they were not legally qualified; for this is indeed a thing highly to be commended, though a Man may labor under a miſtaken Conſcience, that he will not however Sacrifice that Conſcience to any temporal Gain or Advantage; but there were alſo other things that lay heavy upon them, we can prove one of them by unqueſtionable Teſtimony to have been then, and ſtill to be a Perſon zealouſly diſaffected to the Government both in Church and State, a perſonal and profeſt Enemy to the four laſt Kings by Name, a great Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifier of the Commonwealth Form of Government, and a Publick Slanderer even at this time, of the greateſt and moſt uſeful Perſonages of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And I deſire it may be conſidered, that he that would now ſo ſain ſupplant and eject me, was himſelf ejected for no other Reaſon, but becauſe in a Printed Sermon he had publickly owned, aſſerted and defended the Horrid Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr. For it is certain, after his Ejectment, that by the great Application of his Friends in his behalf, he had been reſtored again had it not been for this one thing; but this Sermon being ſhewn, not by me, who knew nothing of it at that time, but by others to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> and by him communicated to the King himſelf, this was the true and the only Reaſon why he was not reſtored, he having conformed to the Church of <hi>England</hi> for ſome time before.</p>
            <p>Now, my Lord, it is true, that the Act of Oblivion had forgiven him this Fault; but yet this hinders not but it might be a very good Reaſon why the King would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him in his particular Service: And I do not ſee how he can be reſtored, not only without diſowning the King's Power of Viſitation, but alſo without a very favorable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect upon that execrable Fault, for which he ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred his Majeſties diſpleaſure, as to be ejected out of his Place.</p>
            <p>Indeed if the Man were in any extreme Neceſſity, there might be ſome Pity due to his Relief, and if he could prove
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106987:31"/> any legal Property in ſuch a Place as this, God forbid but every Man ſhould enjoy his Right; but he can prove no Title, unleſs he firſt prove that the King hath no Right or Power of Viſitation, and he is ſo far from being by his Ejectment in a worſe Condition than he was before, that he got very conſiderably by it, for he had a Living, which is a Freehold in Law beſtowed upon him, of twice the yearly value, and a Living at ſuch a diſtance, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church would not ſuffer him to enjoy both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, if the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> were a Cure of Souls, as in Law I muſt confeſs it is not; but it is ſufficient that it is in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and he for that Reaſon, if he had any Conſcience, might be aſhamed to pretend to both of theſe Places toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> had been a Cure of Souls, he would have loſt his Title to it, immediately upon his Inſtitution and Induction into the other; and it is ſtrange that ſo little regard ſhould be had to the Reaſon of that Law, which was the impoſſibility of a Man's taking ſufficient care of two Places at ſo great a diſtance, as that he ſhould be thought a fit Perſon to be reſtored, after having been ſo fairly and ſo le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally ejected by him that had an unqueſtionable Right to do it; and for a Reaſon in which all the Royal Family is ſo ſenſibly concerned, that he muſt have very little Reſpect for the Memory of our paſt Kings, or for the Perſons of our preſent moſt Gracious, moſt Happy, and Auſpicious King and Queen, notwithſtanding that Crime ſtill bleeding, (like the Blood of the Martyr, which never yet was ſtanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) for which he was ejected, that will pretend to reſtore and reinſtate him again in ſuch Circumſtances as theſe.</p>
            <p>And if to all this we add his groſs neglect of his Duty, while he officiated in our Houſe, his not burying the Dead, not viſiting the Sick, not reſiding upon or near the Place, his ſlubbering over even after his Conformity, the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our Church after an unſeemly and ungainly manner, and after all, his getting little or nothing by his being reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, (for he muſt find a Curate in one place) but only the Satisfaction and Gratification of a cauſeleſs Malice, againſt one that contributed nothing to his Ejectment, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106987:31"/> as I do humbly hope to your Lordſhip, that I have not only all the Law, but all the Equity and Fairneſs in the World on my ſide; and how much more unconſcionable muſt it then needs be thought, when there are ſo many things to be ſaid in my behalf, and when I have ſupplied both for above this year and half, that I ſhould not receive one penny all this while upon the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> Account: But that this Man ſhould receive the Money I have earned, and which neither he nor any of his Friends dare ever yet pretend to be his due.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I have but two things more to add, and I have done, I beg your Lordſhip's Pardon for detaining you ſo long, and will be very brief in what remains.</p>
            <p>My Lord, that excellent Perſon, Mr. Serjeant <hi>Pemberton,</hi> in his Opinion given under his Hand upon this very Caſe of ours, hath theſe very words which follow; <hi>I conceive that the Court of Aldermen being the Perſons who authoriſed the Governors of this Hoſpital by their Order, when the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the City of</hi> London <hi>was diſſolved by the Judgment in the</hi> quo Warranto, <hi>the Authority of thoſe Governors of the Hoſpital ceaſed, and they cannot act again without a new Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Appointment of the Court of Aldermen, and I conceive the King's (that is, King</hi> Jame's) <hi>Proclamation in</hi> October 1688, <hi>doth not give any Authority to the former Governers of the Hoſpital to act by the former Authority to them given, by the former Order of the Court of Aldermen, but they ought to be commiſſionated by a new Order before they act as Governors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then the Governors which were ejected could not be reſtored without a new Order of the Court of Aldermen, the ſame muſt be granted likewiſe of the Officers too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they both acted by the ſame Authority, they were both ejected by the ſame, and it is the ſame that muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them both; and accordingly it muſt be confeſſed, my Lord, that they were both of them reſtored by the Court of Aldermen, commonly ſo called; but the queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that were a legal Court of Aldermen or no, and to this I anſwer, that it was not then, in the expreſs Judgment of the Act of Parliament it ſelf, neither is it to this very
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106987:32"/> day; and I am ſo well perſuaded, that this is effectually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a Paper lately publiſhed, and Entituled, <hi>Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Act of Parliament, for reverſing the Judgment in a</hi> quo Warranto <hi>againſt the City of</hi> London; that when I ſee that Paper ſubſtantially anſwered, which I do particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge the Defendant's Council to do, I will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent not only to loſe my Place and my Arrears, but to ſuffer any other Puniſhment or Diſgrace, and I hope the Parliament when they meet will not only excuſe but juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Author of it, as well for the clearneſs and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingneſs of the thing it ſelf, as that it tends to vindicate and aſſert the Honor and Reputation of that Auguſt Aſſembly, and to the Publick Good of the Nation. But let that be as it will, there are ſeveral worthy Gentlemen that have put in their Claims as well to the Chair it ſelf, as to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Seats in the Court of Aldermen, which during the avoidance of the Charter they relinquiſh'd. Now if there were nothing elſe but this to be conſidered, it is impoſſible to determine in favor of the Defendants, till it be firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd in a judicial way, as it now lies before your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> or by the Parliament it ſelf, who are the beſt Expoſitors of their own Senſe and Meaning, whether this be a legal Court of Aldermen or no; for I ſuppoſe it will be confeſs'd on all ſides, that without the lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Court of Aldermen be firſt of all admitted, there can be no legal Governors or Officers by their appointment, though we ſay they would have been illegal though the Court of Aldermen had been never ſo legal, becauſe they cannot by an inferior and delegated Power reverſe the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Act of the Supreme, and the Act of Parliament Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms none of their Acts, but ſuch as would have been le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, had the Authority been ſo, and not otherwiſe, and ſuch as could not without iniquity and inconvenience be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, as will appear to any Man who ſhall peruſe it; ſo that I think upon the whole matter, there never was a more weak and ſhamefully defenceleſs Cauſe from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World to this very moment in which I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor will be again from this very moment, till the laſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106987:32"/> Trumpet ſhall Sound, a Reſurrection at the Conſummation of all things.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which I intend to ſpeak to, and with which I ſhall conclude, ſhall be their Majeſties gracious Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Twenty Third of <hi>May</hi> in the Year 1689, and in the Firſt Year of their moſt glorious and happy Reign, for Encouragement of Officers, Seamen and Mariners em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the preſent Service: In the laſt Clauſe of which it is provided in theſe Words, <hi>That the Moyety of our Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals in</hi> England, <hi>employed for the Cure of wounded and ſick People, be reſerved during the time of War at Sea, for ſuch as ſhall be wounded in the Service of the Navy, as they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come void from and after the Firſt Day of</hi> June <hi>next,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>Where we ſee not only that their Majeſties claim a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the ſaid Hoſpitals, by calling them <hi>our Hoſpitals;</hi> but as ſuch, by virtue of their Proprietary Power, it being of the liberty of Proprietors to do what they will with their own, they appoint that one Moyety thereof ſhould be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the Sick, Maim'd, and Wounded in their particular Service, which without a legal Propriety they could no more do, than by Law they could quarter Soldiers upon private Houſes without the conſent of the owners: If theſe Houſes be the City's, and not the King's, then the King cannot quarter Soldiers upon them; and much leſs Maintain and Cure them out of their Revenues without the conſent of the City, but this Order asks no leave of the Lord May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or or Court of Aldermen, or of the Citizens and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the City, but relies wholly upon its own Authority, and appoints a Moyety to be reſerved, as their Majeſties due, whenever they pleaſe to claim it, and they might have claimed more if they had ſo pleaſed, and may do it as often as occaſion ſhall require; ſo that all the queſtion is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Order be legal or no, for upon Suppoſition that it is, then the Hoſpital is the King's and not the City's, otherwiſe than by way of Truſt and Delegation, but yet ſo as that the King may at all times command to be done therein, ſo the Intention of the Charity which was for ſick and wounded People be not infringed, whatſoever he thinks
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106987:33"/> for his Service; that the Lords of the Council were of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion it was legal, is plain, becauſe they cauſed it to be Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an Order of the ſame date, which is Printed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it; and I dare ſay, it will be granted to be a much greater Exerciſe of Regal and Viſitatorial Power, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt and ſpend the whole Revenue of the ſame, upon Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Majeſties particular appointment, than to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a few Officers and Tenders to look after them, which is all that we pretend to, the Groſs and Subſtance of thoſe great Charities, being conſumed upon the Patients, whoſe Servants and the King's we are.</p>
            <p>Thus, my Lord, I have undertook to defend the Rights and Prerogatives of this Imperial Crown, ſo far as this Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is concerned, againſt thoſe that at the Hoſpital Charge, and out of the King's proper Revenue are come hither to defeat and overthrow it; an Attempt ſo Loyal, that it may deſerve to be conſidered, even though in your Lordſhip's Judgment I ſhould not have proved all that I pretend to do, which yet I humbly hope I have done. I have made it a part of my Buſineſs to evince as well as I could, upon what very juſt and reaſonable Grounds the Regulations in the time of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> II. were made, and that it was not only the Monarchy and the Prerogative, but the Honor and Intereſt of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them. My Lord, Unity is neceſſary in all Places for the due Adminiſtration and Management of Affairs, but no where more than in ſuch an Houſe as this, where not only the credit of ſo Magnificent and Princely a Bequeſt, but even the Lives of the Patients, and the Succeſs of their Cures do more or leſs depend upon the good underſtanding of the Governors, and the Officers and Servants, with each other, to ſay nothing of the peace and comfortable Living of the Officers within the Houſe among themſelves.</p>
            <p>I am ſo much of this mind, that though I believe it will be eaſily granted, that I am no great Friend to the Power of the Diſſenters; yet for the good of the Houſe, whatever becomes of me, I had rather ſee all the Officers Quakers, or Anabaptiſts, or of any other Tribe belonging to the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106987:33"/> than not all Communicants of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and without pretending to Prophecy, I can eaſily fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, that ſuch a mixture as this will always be inconſiſtent with the peace of the Houſe, and will be the occaſion of endleſs and remedileſs Feuds and Animoſities among us. The Privy Council, who have referred this buſineſs to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip have in effect already determined in our Favor, by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering their Majeſties Declaration of the Twenty Third of <hi>May</hi> above mentioned to be Printed, which Declaration im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies rather a greater Power than we have need of for our Defence and Protection, and I hope your Lordſhip will ſee Reaſon to follow their Example. My Lord, your Lordſhip is not only Lord Chief Juſtice of their Majeſties Court of <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> but you have alſo another Title, you are Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore I ſhall humbly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate with your Lordſhip, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did with the Judge of all the Earth. <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Land do right, that be far from thee, to ſlay the righteous with the wicked, and that the righteous ſhould be as the wicked,</hi> to make no diſtinction betwixt right and wrong, <hi>that be far from thee to do after this manner.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon_extracts">
            <head>
               <hi>Some Choice Collections out of a SERMON, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, Magiſtracy, God's Miniſtry; Or a Rule for the Rulers and Peoples due Correſpondence, Preached at the Midſummer Aſſizes at</hi> Abingdon, <hi>Anno 1651. By</hi> W. Hughes.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE Stile of the Dedication—To his Excellency the Lord <hi>Cromwel,</hi> General of all the Forces raiſed by the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Epiſtle Dedicatory it ſelf—I am not conſcious that this Diſcourſe hath cauſe to bluſh ſave for its Author's
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106987:34"/> Weakneſs—<hi>What think you, Sir, of his and his Diſcourſe's Wickedneſs too? It ſeems it is not Crimes will make you bluſh, only you are ſorry to find your ſelf a Bungler in the Trade of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and you bluſh only for that Reaſon, becauſe your Pen can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tranſcribe the Wickedneſs of your Heart.</hi> There was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Modeſty in this Confeſſion however.</p>
               <p>A little after concerning his Patron, he ſays—Methinks 'tis pity genuine Merit ſhould not have its due reported, when the Picture of it hath even been adored, but that your Thoughts reply in ſilence, <hi>he whom the Lord Commendeth,</hi> and Works do eccho thereto louder than to need our Words.</p>
               <p>'Tis deſired that God would lead you in this way even to your Journeys end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> Concerning his Diſcourſe or fardle of Treaſon, he ſays—The Subject of it is the ready Road your Honor doth and is to walk in—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> It is the ſuit of many Hearts, that your Honor having now ſubdued our Enemies, would put on further to make the Godly Friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> My Lord, I have adventur'd far upon your Favor, it is enough and over for me, (will your Lordſhip only but excuſe me) whilſt by this I tell the World, <hi>(take notice World, and remember what he ſays againſt another Day)</hi> that as I have been for Chriſt's Intereſt and the Commonwealths ſometimes under your Command; I am, and ever ſhall be, my Lord,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Honor's Faithful Servant to be Commanded, W. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Out of the Preface to the Reader—'Tis too well known our Body Politick hath been much diſtempered, and the Grief ſcarce cured yet: my aim I'm ſure is right to heal the Sore, however I hit the mark.—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> Former Injuſtice, <hi>(in the Reign of King</hi> Charles I,) and preſent Diſobedience, <hi>(againſt proſperous Rebels)</hi> look like Competitors, who ſhould be greateſt—That <hi>(former juſtice)</hi> through mercy we are fairly quit of, I wiſh it were improved to ſend this <hi>(preſent Diſobedience)</hi> packing after.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106987:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> How quick it <hi>(Diſobedience)</hi> theives, how far it ſpreads, and what a Crop it bears, laſt Harveſt told us here at Home, although the righteous, gracious Lord, would have it ripe and rotten together: 'Tis time Men ſhould be wiſer now than to <hi>kick againſt the pricks,</hi> oe <hi>labor</hi> any longer <hi>for the wind</hi>—All this Diſobedience he ſpeaks of was the Diſobedience of <hi>Charles</hi> II. and his Malignant Adherents againſt his Patron <hi>Oliver,</hi> and the Sovereign Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which is here pointed at in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and like a true Prophet, he tells you, it was in vain to contend any longer for that baffled Intereſt; for that it was but kicking againſt the pricks, and laboring for the wind; that is, in other words, What a fine King's Chaplain is this Man like to make in his Majeſties Royal Hoſpital of St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Southwark?</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second ſhall never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.—</p>
               <p>He concludes this worthy Preface with theſe Words.—Reader, Three of the Famous Monarchies of the World are down; the Miſcellany Fourth, ſure is ſetting, make way the Fifth, the Everlaſting one may riſe upon us.—I could expoſe his Miſcellany Fourth, but this would be <hi>aliud agere,</hi> we are not now interpreting of Propheſies; the Four great Monarchies He ſpeaks of, were the <hi>Babylonian, Medo-Perſian, Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi> the three firſt he tells us are gone, and the laſt crumbled and divided into ſeveral and diſtinct <hi>Dynaſties</hi> is declining, or in other words, Monarchy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and its Dependences is clearly gone, and he hopes to ſee it ſo every where elſe in a very ſhort time; ſo that if a Man would give the World to ſee a Monarch, there ſhould be no ſuch Creature any where to be found, and then <hi>make way the Fifth,</hi> wherein Chriſt according to this Man's fancy, wherein he wants not the Concurrence of a very ancient, but a very ſilly, phantaſtical and ſenſeleſs Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, was to reign upon Earth a thouſand Years, and then Mr. <hi>H.</hi> was like to be a great Man, for the Saints, that is, the Independents were to reign together with him, though Mr. <hi>Venner</hi> and his Party were of another mind, they thought the Anabaptiſts were to be the Men. When that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106987:35"/> time comes we ſhall know more, in the mean while we may ſee what a ſpecial Friend to Monarchy we have of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and how well qualified this Phanatick is to eat the Bread of Kings. But this was very ill tim'd of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> after an Epiſtle to <hi>O. C.</hi> who juſt about this time had a Month's mind to be a Monarch himſelf, and did actually propoſe it to his great Confident and Favourite <hi>Whitlock,</hi> as the only means to put an end to thoſe Confuſions into which the Commonwealth Principles and Deſigns had brought them, and <hi>Whitlock</hi> very honeſtly and very wiſely adviſed him, to reſtore his lawful King, as the beſt and only means to put an end to thoſe Confuſions, and the moſt conducible to his own Honor and Safety, but had no thanks for his pains, as the Story is largely repreſented by himſelf in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate and excellent Memoirs.</p>
               <p>As for the Sermon it ſelf, to mention every thing that is obnoxious in it, would be to tranſcribe it all, therefore I ſhall ſet down only two notable Paſſages, leaving the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to make his own Paraphraſe upon them: The firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the Tryal and Condemnation of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. by the pretended High Court of Juſtice, which he ſhows us was not ſo bad a thing, as ſome would make it, and by ſeveral very pleaſant Compariſons endeavors to make the Murther and Depoſition of Princes ſo eaſie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, that the moſt ſqueamiſh of his Readers may digeſt it.—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12, 13.—3. <hi>Conclus.</hi>—3. All unuſual are not ſtrait unwarrantable Courſes, although of late leſs beaten Paths have been walked in, it follows not that 'tis a Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs preſently: What will you ſay to <hi>Phinchas</hi> Numb. 25. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 30. <hi>who executed judgment upon</hi> Zimri? The one a Prince, the other but a Prieſt; and ſo no Magiſtrate, nor commiſſioned from him, that may be clearly found; not that ſuch Inſtances are always, or in all things imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: yet, 1. Where Circumſtances do concur, the Plea is ſomewhat ſtrengthened that's drawn after ſo fair a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, that brought Gods <hi>Approbation</hi> to the <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primatur</hi> to the <hi>Action.</hi> 2. A <hi>minori,</hi> if a <hi>private</hi> Man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106987:35"/> an Hearing, &amp;c. much more a <hi>Supreme Court</hi> by <hi>fair Proceedings,</hi> and yet that Action of the Parliament is not without Precedent neither, and therefore not ſo uncouth as ſome do render it: Indeed I look that peeviſh Spirits will be angry that I tell them ſo, although the Sober may accept it as a Courteſie; for whoſe ſakes are the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſtances. <hi>Tarquinius Superbius</hi> the Seventh and laſt King of <hi>Rome</hi> was expell'd, and Monarchy thence toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him. <hi>Nero</hi> the Sixth Emperor of <hi>Rome</hi> was by the Senate declared an Enemy, and condemned to be Whipt to Death. <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> was depoſed by the Eloctors. <hi>Richard</hi> tho Second, King of <hi>England,</hi> was depoſed by Parliament, and after Famiſh'd in <hi>Pomfret</hi> Caſtle. <hi>Athaliah</hi> the Queen was ſlain by the Officers and Captains, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. <hi>Amaziah</hi> tho King, after he forſook the Lord, was Executed, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25. Which I only mention, to the end Mens Diſcontents might once be ended.—O rare Hoſpitaller!</p>
               <p>The other Paſſage is concerning tho Miniſters that were ejected by thoſe Impudent Fellows tho Tryers, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fault for the moſt part, but only being ſcandalous for Learning, Loyalty, or ſome other Virtue, and many times all Virtues in Conjunction together; he preſſeth tho vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Proſecution of ſo good and uſeful a Deſign, and that you may ſee he was through-paced, and flinch'd at nothing: he recommends Coblers and Tinkers, and other Lay Divines well furniſh'd with Confidence, and well appointed with Lungs to be preſented to Livings, in the room of thoſe Bookiſh, Human-Learning, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical, Antichriſtian Theologues that were ejected; his words are theſe, <hi>p.</hi> 17, 18. 3. Encouraging an able Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Miniſtry for them, your ſelves and for the Nation—from firſt to laſt ordinarily; there neither hath been not is any true Converſion, without an outward Miniſtry; to paſs by others, the ſad Prophaneſs on the the one hand, Blaſphemous Hereſies on the other, or groſs Ignorance on them both; are Arguments enough and over to convince us of the Neceſſity of ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106987:36"/> But God forbid my Mouth ſhould open for thoſe whoſe Mouths are ſhut. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Silenc'd Clergy-men.</hi>
                  </note> Dumb Dogs the Scripture calls them, or that I ſhould Pronounce one word in their behalf, whoſe wicked Converſation doth, as it were, Renounce the Goſpel they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>he that labors not,</hi> or not to purpoſe, <hi>let him not eat.</hi> I humbly beg that thoſe commiſſioned <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Tryers.</hi>
                  </note> to that purpoſe would be active and impartial, as to find out, ſo to turn out ſuch; that if they do no good, you may prevent them from doing hurt. We are ſure there is a Neſt of ſuch about the Country, but where the Fault is, whether becauſe the People will not inform or thoſe impowered not reform, I cannot ſay; whatever others may ſuſpect; nor is my purpoſe to confine this neceſſarily to a Coat; our Hearts as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, <hi>would all the Lords people were Prophets;</hi> ſo then, that thoſe found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy-and approved for the Work, be rewarded in it: Chriſt ſaith <hi>the Laborer is worthy of his hire,</hi> which is meant of a Goſpel Miniſter, <hi>(whether he be ſent or no)</hi> O brave King's Chaplain, O fine Mr. <hi>Hughes. Euge,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>!</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:106987:36"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is Affidavit made before one of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Juſtices of the Peace, and one of the Governors of St. <hi>Thomas Hoſpital,</hi> that Dr. <hi>T.</hi> the preſent pretended Phyſician of that <hi>Houſe</hi> did in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 88. a little before the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (our preſent gracious Sovereign) arriv'd at <hi>London,</hi> or the Government which was then in great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, was ſettled, declare it as his Senſe, ſpeaking of the four laſt Kings, that they were Rogues and Raſcals, and that we had better be govern'd by a Commonwealth, or a State, as in other Countries than by any of them.—And we have other things of a like ſeditious Nature, that ſhall be afterwards proved againſt him, if there be occaſion, or if he wants to have them proved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaere.</hi> Whether ſuch a true <hi>Trojan</hi> to Monarchy as this, be not very fit to receive the King's Pay in a Royal Foundation? And whether he and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chaplain are not very finely pair'd?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
